Today's lecture topic will be about regularization
오늘 강의 주제는 정규화와 최적화에 관한 내용입니다.
and optimization, which are two very important concepts more
이 두 개념은 딥러닝과 머신러닝
broadly in deep learning and machine learning,
전반에서 매우 중요하지만, 특히 컴퓨터
but especially important for computer vision.
비전 분야에서 중요합니다.
And we're going to start with a recap from last week
우리는 지난주 내용을 간단히
and discuss some of the topics that we discussed last time.
복습하고, 그때 다뤘던 주제들을 다시 논의할 것입니다.
So we really honed in on this idea
우리는 컴퓨터 비전의 핵심 과제인
of image classification as a core task in computer vision.
이미지 분류에 대해 집중적으로 살펴보았습니다.
And what this task is is given an image as input,
이 과제는 입력으로 주어진 이미지를
you try to map this image to a label inside of a set of labels.
레이블 집합 내의 하나의 레이블로 매핑하는 것입니다.
So here we have five different labels, cat, dog, bird, deer,
여기에는 다섯 가지 레이블이 있습니다: 고양이, 개, 새, 사슴, 그리고
and truck.
트럭입니다.
And the goal is to assign the correct label
목표는 입력 이미지에 올바른 레이블을
to the input image.
할당하는 것입니다.
And you're creating some model or some function
이미지를 입력으로 받아
that takes an image as input and outputs the specific label here.
특정 레이블을 출력하는 모델이나 함수를 만드는 것이죠.
And we also talked about a lot of the challenges
또한 분류의 여러 도전 과제에
for classification.
대해서도 이야기했습니다.
So one of the main challenges is shown in the top left here,
가장 큰 도전 과제 중 하나는 왼쪽 위에
but it's this idea of the semantic gap between what
나와 있는데, 인간이 이미지에서
we as humans perceive in the image, which is the cat,
인지하는 의미(예:
and what it's actually represented
고양이)와 컴퓨터가
in the computer, which is this grid of pixel values
표현하는 방식(픽셀 값의 격자, 다차원
where you have this multidimensional array
배열 또는 텐서, 각
or tensor, and you have discrete values for each of the pixels.
픽셀의 이산 값) 사이의 의미적 간극입니다.
This is very different from how we're perceiving the image
이것은 우리가 이미지를 보고 고양이라고
and just deciding that this is a cat.
판단하는 방식과 매우 다릅니다.
So being able to map from this complex numeric representation
복잡한 수치 표현을 인간이 이해할 수 있는 형태로
into one that we humans understand
매핑하는 것이 핵심
is the core challenge here.
도전 과제입니다.
But also there's challenges surrounding the images
또한 이미지 자체와 관련된 도전 과제도
themselves.
있습니다.
So if you look at something like the illumination of the scene,
예를 들어, 장면의 조명 상태를 보면, 조명이
so here you'll have different pixel intensities
어디에 있느냐에 따라
based on where the lighting is in the scene.
픽셀 강도가 달라집니다.
Also you could have certain parts of your object
또한 객체의 일부가 그림자에 가려져서
are in the shade and harder to see.
보기 어려울 수도 있습니다.
Cats by nature are very deformable,
고양이는 본질적으로 변형이
so you talk about deformable objects that can move around
가능한 동물이기 때문에, 움직이고 구부러지며
and twist and bend in different ways,
다양한 형태를 가질 수 있어
so they won't always have the same shape.
항상 같은 모양을 갖지 않습니다.
And this can prove challenging if you're
이것은 객체를 탐지하는
trying to design an algorithm to detect objects.
알고리즘을 설계할 때 어려움을 줍니다.
There's also the challenge of occlusion.
가림 현상(occlusion)도 도전 과제입니다.
So you could have a cat that's hiding underneath the cushions
예를 들어, 고양이가 쿠션 밑에 숨었을 때,
here, but we as a human can clearly
인간은 꼬리가 보이기
tell it's a cat because of the tail, how it's sticking up
때문에 고양이라는 것을 명확히 알 수
at the end here.
있습니다.
And then the way that cats behave,
고양이의 행동 방식으로도
we can infer that this is a cat.
고양이라는 것을 추론할 수 있죠.
You'll also have things like background clutter, where
배경 잡음(background clutter)도
the object could blend into the background.
있어서 객체가 배경과 섞여 보일 수 있습니다.
So we need to account for this somehow as well.
이 부분도 고려해야 합니다.
And finally, there's this idea of intraclass variation, where
마지막으로, 같은 카테고리 내에서도 객체들이 매우 다르게 보일 수 있는
different objects in the same category
클래스 내 변이(intraclass
can look very different from each other,
variation) 문제가 있습니다.
but we still need to group them all into the same category.
하지만 우리는 이들을 같은 카테고리로 묶어야 합니다.
So here are a lot of just the challenges of recognition,
이처럼 인식 문제에는 많은
and why it isn't such a simple problem where you can just
도전 과제가 있으며, 단순히 if-else
write if else rules to account for everything, and just
규칙이나 간단한 논리만으로
simple logic to classify.
해결할 수 없습니다.
So if logic is thrown out the window,
논리가 통하지
you can't just create these logic rules,
않는다면, 어떻게
how do you actually create a classifier?
분류기를 만들 수 있을까요?
Here's where we talked about data-driven approaches.
여기서 데이터 기반 접근법을 이야기했습니다.
And we talked about, basically, the simplest machine
가장 단순한 머신러닝 모델인 k-최근접 이웃(k-nearest
learning model, which is this k-nearest neighbors model.
neighbors) 모델에 대해 설명했습니다.
And the idea is that you look for a given data point, what
이 모델은 새로운 데이터 포인트가 들어왔을 때,
are the existing data points in your training set
훈련 세트 내에서 가장 가까운
that are very close in distance to your new data point
데이터 포인트들을 찾아 그들의 레이블을 참조하는
coming in.
방식입니다.
And for the 1-nearest neighbor case, this just results in--
1-최근접 이웃의 경우 가장 가까운 데이터 포인트
you find the closest data point, you assign it that class label.
하나를 찾아 그 레이블을 할당합니다.
And you can also look at multiple nearest neighbors where
또한 여러 개의 최근접 이웃을 보고
you're assigning the most common class label among those nearest
그 중 가장 많은 레이블을 할당하는 방법도
neighbors.
있습니다.
So we talked about these two different approaches.
이 두 가지 접근법에 대해 이야기했습니다.
We talked about how you ideally, don't
데이터 세트를 단순히 훈련과 테스트로
want to split your data set into train and test,
나누는 대신, 훈련,
but you can do train validation and test,
검증, 테스트로 나누어 검증
so that you can use this validation set here
세트를 통해 하이퍼파라미터를
to actually help you choose your hyperparameters.
선택하는 것이 이상적이라고 했습니다.
So the main hyperparameter for k-nearest neighbors
k-최근접 이웃의 주요 하이퍼파라미터는 k
is this k, 1 or 5 in these examples.
값이며, 예를 들어 1이나 5가 될 수 있습니다.
And what we showed is an example where
여기서 보여드린
you're plotting what is your accuracy on this validation set
예는, 이 검증 세트에서의 정확도를 다양한
here over the different k values here.
k 값에 대해 플로팅한 것입니다.
And you would choose the one that has the highest accuracy.
그리고 가장 높은 정확도를 가진 값을 선택하시면 됩니다.
So this is how you use the validation set,
이렇게 검증 세트를 사용하고, 이
and then you would reserve this test set for--
테스트 세트는 완전히 새로운
OK, how does your model do on completely new data
데이터에 대해 모델이 어떻게 작동하는지
it's never seen before?
평가하는 데 남겨둡니다.
That would be the purpose of the test set.
이것이 테스트 세트의 목적입니다.
This is all just recap.
이것들은 모두 복습입니다.
There was a bit of confusion about distance metrics.
거리 측정법에 대해 약간 혼란이 있었죠.
We put a post on Ed that explains this in more detail.
Ed에 좀 더 자세히 설명한 글을 올렸습니다.
But we talked about two different distance metrics.
우리는 두 가지 다른 거리 측정법에 대해 이야기했습니다.
The most two commonly used ones in machine learning,
머신러닝에서 가장 흔히 쓰이는 두
which are the Manhattan distance or L1 distance and L2 distance
가지는 Manhattan 거리, 즉 L1 거리와 L2
or Euclidean distance.
거리, 즉 유클리드 거리입니다.
L2 distance is like if you imagine just the straight line
L2 거리는 직선 거리로, 우리가
distance--
일상에서 거리라고
how we think of distance in everyday usage
생각하는 바로 그
of the word geometrically.
기하학적 거리입니다.
And then Manhattan distance is this idea where you can only
Manhattan 거리는 이 그림에서처럼 좌우와
traverse left and right and up and down in this diagram,
상하로만 이동할 수 있고 대각선으로는 이동할
and you can't move diagonally.
수 없는 개념입니다.
So specifically looking at just one quick example here.
한 가지 예를 빠르게 보겠습니다.
The reason why all these points on the line
이 선 위의 모든 점이
are the same distance from the origin
원점에서 같은 거리에 있는 이유는
here is because you can't move diagonally,
대각선으로 이동할 수 없기 때문에, 여기서는
so you have to move in this case up 0.5 and to the right 0.5,
위로 0.5, 오른쪽으로 0.5만 이동해야 해서 총 거리가
so the total distance is 1, whereas here you're
1이 되는 겁니다. 반면에 여기서는
just going a straight line but it's 1 also.
직선으로 이동하지만 역시 거리가 1입니다.
The same distance here.
같은 거리라는 뜻입니다.
Whereas in the L2 distance, all the points
반면 L2 거리에서는 원점에서 같은 거리에
equidistant from the origin here form a circle
있는 모든 점이 원을 이루는데,
because you can just go in the direct line here.
이는 직선으로 바로 갈 수 있기 때문입니다.
So this is maybe a brief explanation.
이것이 간단한 설명입니다.
The final thing we honed in on last time
지난 시간에 집중했던 마지막 주제는
was this idea of a linear classifier.
선형 분류기라는 개념이었습니다.
So the basic idea in the basic setting that we did
기본적인 설정에서 우리가 한 것은,
is we have an image, which is say, width 32 and height 32,
예를 들어 너비 32, 높이 32인 이미지가
and there are three pixel values for each
있고, 이미지의 각 공간 위치마다
of the spatial locations in our image representing
빨강, 초록, 파랑 강도를
the red, green, and blue intensities forming the color.
나타내는 세 가지 픽셀 값이 있다는 겁니다.
And the idea is we take this array of numbers for our image,
그리고 이 이미지의 숫자 배열을
and we flatten it out into an array of just 3,000 different
3,072개의 숫자로
numbers, 3,072.
평탄화(flatten)합니다.
And then we are multiplying this vector by our weight matrix W.
그 다음에 이 벡터를 가중치 행렬 W와 곱합니다.
And the basic idea is if we have a weight matrix W that has
기본 아이디어는, 가중치 행렬 W가
a height here of 10 and then the width is 3,071,
높이 10, 너비 3,072일 때, 이 행렬의 각 행을
we're multiplying each of these rows by our input sample x.
입력 샘플 x와 곱한다는 것입니다.
And this will give us 10 resulting class scores.
그러면 10개의 클래스 점수가 나오게 됩니다.
So oftentimes we'll add a bias term
종종 각 클래스마다 하나씩
as well, which would just be 1 bias term for each class.
1개의 바이어스 항을 더하기도 합니다.
So this would be a size 10 vector here.
이 바이어스 항은 크기 10인 벡터가 됩니다.
And we also talked about three different ways
그리고 우리는 이러한 선형 모델을 바라보거나
you can view or think about these linear models.
생각할 수 있는 세 가지 다른 방법에 대해서도 이야기했습니다.
One is the algebraic viewpoint, which I described here,
하나는 대수학적 관점인데,
where each row is represented-- independently
여기서 각 행이 독립적으로 클래스를 나타내는
representing the class.
방식입니다.
And you multiply it by the input vector x, you get your score
그리고 입력 벡터 x에 곱하면 점수를 얻고, 편향을
and you add the bias to get your final score.
더해 최종 점수를 구합니다.
And you do each row independently in the sense.
각 행을 독립적으로 처리하는 의미입니다.
You can also view these learned class weights here
또한 여기 학습된 클래스 가중치를 템플릿으로 볼 수도
as templates where if we then reravel
있는데, 벡터를 원래 이미지 형태로
the vector into the original shape of the image,
다시 펼치면 강도를 시각화해서 각
we could plot the intensities here and understand what
클래스별 템플릿이 무엇인지 이해할 수
is the, template per class, which is what
있습니다. 이것이 바로 이 시각화가
this visualization represents.
나타내는 바입니다.
And then the final way you can think
마지막으로
about it is a geometric viewpoint, where
생각할 수 있는 방법은 기하학적
each of these rows in our weight matrix
관점으로, 가중치 행렬의 각
are represented by these lines here in our input space.
행이 입력 공간에서 이 선들로 표현됩니다.
And specifically, the line is where
특히 이 선은
we set this equation to 0, which is the decision boundary.
방정식을 0으로 설정한 결정 경계입니다.
So this forms the point where above the line
그래서 이 선 위쪽에서는 양수 점수를,
you could have a positive score, and below the line
아래쪽에서는 음수 점수를
you would have a negative score for the class.
해당 클래스에 대해 가질 수 있는 지점이 형성됩니다.
So these are the different viewpoints
이것들이 선형 모델을 보는
or for how you can view these linear models.
다양한 관점들입니다.
They're all doing the same thing.
모두 같은 일을 하고 있습니다.
And one nice thing about the geometric viewpoint
기하학적 관점의 좋은 점은 데이터를
is that if you visualize your data, like, say, you
시각화했을 때, 예를 들어 파란색과
want to classify blue versus red here,
빨간색을 분류하려고 할 때, 데이터를
it's very easy to tell that you can't draw a line that perfectly
완벽하게 분리하는 선을 그을 수 없다는 것을
separates the data here.
쉽게 알 수 있다는 겁니다.
So it's nice way you can gain intuition
그래서 선형 모델이 할 수 있는
about what is possible for linear model to do.
것에 대한 직관을 얻기에 좋은 방법입니다.
OK.
좋습니다.
I think that's the high-level recap
지난 시간에 논의한 내용을
of what we discussed last time.
고수준에서 다시 정리한 것입니다.
I'll actually be going into a little bit more detail
이제 이번 강의의 새로운 내용에
on the new content for this lecture now,
대해 좀 더 자세히 설명할 텐데, 지난 시간이나 이번
but I just wanted to pause briefly
강의 초반에 논의한
if anyone had any questions about what we discussed
내용에 대해 질문이 있으면
last time or at the beginning of this lecture, feel free to ask.
잠시 멈추고 자유롭게 물어보셔도 됩니다.
Yeah.
네.
So the question for those online is for this visual viewpoint,
온라인에 계신 분들의 질문인데, 이 시각적 관점이 k-최근접
is this the same as running k-nearest neighbors?
이웃(k-nearest neighbors)과 같은 건가요?
And this would be maybe one of the neighbors
그리고 비교하는 이웃 중
that you're comparing against?
하나일 수도 있나요?
Are they mathematically equivalent?
수학적으로 동일한가요?
No, they're not the same because these templates
아니요, 같지 않습니다. 이 템플릿들은 이
are formed from this line, so it's not one specific data
선에서 형성되기 때문에 특정 데이터 포인트 하나가
point.
아닙니다.
But you can still calculate the templates based on this--
하지만 이 템플릿들은 계산할 수 있고, 이 그림에서
they would represent more like, if you see in this diagram
보시면 클래스 방향을
here there's the line pointing in the direction of the class,
가리키는 선이 있는데, 이 점을
so it would be representing this point here.
대표한다고 볼 수 있습니다.
Yeah, so the question is, how did we get this 3,072 number?
네, 질문은 이 3,072라는 숫자를 어떻게 얻었느냐는 거죠?
So the idea here is that if the height of our image is 32 pixels
여기서 아이디어는 이미지 높이가 32픽셀, 너비가 32픽셀이고,
and the width is 32 pixels, and then each location in the image
이미지의 각 위치가 빨강, 초록, 파랑 픽셀
is represented by three values, the red, green, and blue pixel
강도 세 값으로 표현되므로, 전체
intensities, we would then get 32 times 32 times 3 total values
이미지를 표현하기 위해 32 곱하기 32 곱하기 3의 총
to represent the entire image.
값이 나온다는 겁니다.
And that's how we get this 3,072 number.
그래서 이 3,072라는 숫자가 나오는 것입니다.
So here's, I guess, very specific example
여기 아주 구체적인 선형
of a linear model here.
모델의 예가 있습니다.
And when we multiply our input x by our weight matrix W,
입력 x에 가중치 행렬 W를 곱하면, 서로 다른
we get the resulting scores for these different classes.
클래스에 대한 점수가 나옵니다.
And you can see that for cat it's
고양이 클래스 점수가 낮은데, 자동차
not doing so well because car has a higher score.
점수가 더 높아서 잘못된 걸 알 수 있습니다.
And we want the highest score for the correct class.
우리는 정답 클래스가 가장 높은 점수를 받길 원합니다.
Also, here on this second example
두 번째 예에서는 제대로
does pretty well because it's doing it correctly.
맞춰서 꽤 잘하고 있죠.
But then in the frog example, it completely wrong,
하지만 개구리 예에서는 완전히 틀렸는데,
where it's by far the lowest score of the three.
세 점수 중 가장 낮습니다.
So intuitively, we can tell that these scores are not very good.
직관적으로 이 점수들이 좋지 않다는 걸 알 수 있습니다.
But how do we mathematically formalize this intuition?
그런데 이 직관을 수학적으로 어떻게 공식화할 수 있을까요?
And how do we determine how good a given model is?
그리고 주어진 모델이 얼마나 좋은지 어떻게 판단할까요?
This is the idea of a loss function, which tells you
이것이 바로 손실 함수(loss function)의 개념인데,
how good or specifically tells you how bad a classifier is.
손실 함수는 분류기가 얼마나 좋은지, 더 정확히는 얼마나 나쁜지를 알려줍니다.
So given a data set of examples where we're indexing with this
예를 들어, i라는 인덱스로 표시된 데이터 세트가 있다고 할
letter i-- we have Xi as each of the training examples,
때, Xi는 각 훈련 예제이고, yi는 각
yi as each of the training labels--
훈련 레이블입니다. 우리는 전체
we can compute the loss over our entire data set,
데이터 세트에 대해 손실을 계산할 수
where we calculate this loss for each training example
있는데, 각 훈련 예제에 대해 이 손실을 모델에 통과시켜
by sending it through our model here, which is this f of XiW.
계산합니다. 여기서 모델은 f(XiW)입니다.
We get our label.
그럼 레이블을 얻습니다.
And then we compute it compared to the ground truth label yi.
그리고 나서 실제 정답 레이블 yi와 비교해서 손실을 계산합니다.
And we just take the average over our whole data set.
그리고 전체 데이터 세트에 대해 평균을 냅니다.
So this is how we do this.
이렇게 해서 손실을 계산하는 겁니다.
We talked about, in last lecture, the Softmax loss
지난 강의에서 다뤘던 Softmax 손실
or the cross-entropy loss, which is the most commonly
또는 교차 엔트로피 손실은 분류에
used loss for classification.
가장 흔히 사용되는 손실 함수입니다.
So I won't discuss that again in so much detail here.
그래서 여기서는 그 내용을 다시 자세히 다루지 않겠습니다.
But basically, it's very high loss
기본적으로, 정답 클래스의 확률을 낮게
when you predict low probability of the correct class.
예측하면 손실이 매우 큽니다.
It's very low loss when you're predicting the correct class
정답 클래스를 매우 높은 확률로
at very high probability.
예측하면 손실이 매우 작습니다.
So this what I just explained is all
제가 방금 설명한 내용은 모두 데이터 손실(data loss)이라고 부르는
contained within what we call the data loss.
것 안에 포함되어 있습니다.
So this is a loss that tells you how
이 손실은 모델의 예측이 훈련 데이터와
well do the model predictions match our training data.
얼마나 잘 맞는지를 알려줍니다.
And obviously, we want this to be very low.
당연히 이 값은 매우 낮아야 합니다.
And if it's very low, it means our model is
낮다는 것은 모델이 훈련 데이터를
fitting our training data well.
잘 맞추고 있다는 의미입니다.
But there's a second component, which I'll discuss today,
하지만 오늘 다룰 두 번째 요소가 있는데, 바로 손실
which is this regularization term of the loss function.
함수의 정규화 항(regularization term)입니다.
So what this does is, is it's intended
이 항은 모델이 훈련 데이터에 너무
to prevent the model from doing too well on the training data.
과적합하는 것을 막기 위한 것입니다.
So it actually does worse on the training data,
그래서 실제로는 훈련 데이터에서 성능이 좀
but the goal is to make it do better on new test data
떨어지지만, 새로운 테스트 데이터나 보지 않은 데이터에서 더
or unseen data.
잘하도록 하는 것이 목표입니다.
So worse on training but better on the test set.
훈련 데이터에서는 성능이 떨어지지만 테스트 세트에서는 더 좋아지는 거죠.
That's the point of regularization.
이것이 정규화의 목적입니다.
And we'll go over a lot of the intuition
다음 슬라이드에서 정규화에
for how to think about it in the next slides here.
대한 직관적인 이해를 많이 다룰 겁니다.
But the high-level goal is to do worse on the training data,
하지만 큰 그림에서 보면, 훈련 데이터에서는 성능이 떨어지더라도
but then better on the test data or just unseen data.
테스트 데이터나 보지 않은 데이터에서 더 잘하는 것이 정규화의 목표입니다.
That's the point of regularization.
바로 이것이 정규화의 핵심입니다.
Yeah, so we're computing the loss
네, 그래서 우리는 i번째 훈련
on each of the i training examples.
샘플 각각에 대해 손실을 계산하고 있습니다.
Yeah, so the loss of the i-th example uses the Xi and the yi.
네, 그래서 i번째 예제의 손실은 Xi와 yi를 사용합니다.
That make sense?
이해가 되시나요?
I mean, you could not have an i here.
즉, 여기서 i가 없어도 됩니다.
But this is just saying that i-th lost [INAUDIBLE].
하지만 이것은 단지 i번째 손실을 말하는 겁니다 [잘 안 들림].
Yeah.
네.
Yeah, you normally don't have a different loss for each i
네, 보통 각 i마다 다른 손실을 가지지는 않습니다,
if that's what you're asking.
그게 질문하신 거라면요.
Yeah, yeah.
네, 맞습니다.
So it's just-- you could just--
그래서 그냥-- 우리는 Li를 i번째
we described Li as the loss for the i-th training example,
훈련 예제의 손실로 설명했으니 여기서 그렇게
so we're just using it here.
사용하고 있습니다.
But yeah, it could be i.
하지만 네, i일 수도 있습니다.
So for regularization, people usually
정규화에 대해 이야기할 때,
have this intuition when thinking about it,
보통 이런 직관을 갖습니다,
where this is a toy example.
이건 단순한 예제입니다.
And the idea is we want to fit some function to these points
아이디어는 입력이 x이고 출력이 y인 함수에 이
where our input is x and our output is y.
점들을 맞추고 싶다는 겁니다.
And you, say, have two different types of models, f1 and f2.
그리고 두 가지 다른 모델, f1과 f2가 있다고 합시다.
And you're trying to decide which of these is better.
그리고 어느 쪽이 더 나은지 결정하려고 합니다.
So f1 goes through all of our data points,
f1은 모든 데이터 포인트를 통과하므로
so the training or the data loss will be very low because it's
훈련 또는 데이터 손실이 매우 낮을 겁니다,
basically doing it perfectly, whereas f2 doesn't go
거의 완벽하게 맞추니까요, 반면 f2는 모든 점을
through every point perfectly.
완벽하게 맞추지는 않습니다.
But intuitively, it feels like, probably, f2
하지만 직관적으로는, 아마도 f2가 우리가 전에
is a better model when we're now testing on new data we've never
본 적 없는 새로운 데이터에서 테스트할 때 더 나은
seen before.
모델일 것 같습니다.
So regularization captures this intuition of you
그래서 정규화는 데이터를 너무 과하게 맞추지 말라는
don't want to overfit your data so hard,
이 직관을 담고 있고, 데이터에
and you might actually be better off with a model
덜 맞지만 더 단순하거나
that fits the data less, but is either simpler or has
다른 특성으로 인해 더 나은 선택이 될 수 있는
some other properties that make it a better choice.
모델이 실제로 더 나을 수 있다는 걸 의미합니다.
And so if we ask, OK, how are these models going
그래서 만약 우리가 묻는다면, 같은 분포 내의 새로운
to do on new data that's within our same distribution?
데이터에 대해 이 모델들이 어떻게 작동할까요?
You'll find that f2 does a much better job at modeling.
f2가 모델링을 훨씬 더 잘하는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
So here's it's doing better on the unseen data.
여기서는 보지 못한 데이터에 대해 더 잘 작동하고 있죠.
So I think, there's also an intuition
이전 예제에서 잘 보여준 직관이
in this previous example that's demonstrated very well where
하나 더 있는데, 우리는 더 단순한
we're preferring simpler models where it's
모델을 선호하는 경향이 있습니다. 이는
like Occam's razor, which is this idea in philosophy
Occam's razor라는 철학적, 과학적 발견의
and also scientific discovery where
개념으로, 여러 경쟁
if you have multiple competing hypotheses,
가설이 있을 때 가장 단순한 가설부터
you should go with the simplest one first
선택하고, 그것이 확실히
and then if you know for sure that's wrong,
틀렸다고 알게 되면 더
then you can start trying out more complicated ones as you go.
복잡한 가설을 시도해보는 것입니다.
But this is maybe also some intuition
이것이 정규화가
you can have for why regularization can be useful.
왜 유용할 수 있는지에 대한 직관이기도 합니다.
And then one final thing about this equation
그리고 아직 언급하지 않은 이
that I didn't touch on yet is this lambda parameter here.
방정식의 마지막 부분은 바로 이 lambda 파라미터입니다.
So this is the regularization strength, which
이것은 정규화 강도, 즉 또 다른
is another hyperparameter.
하이퍼파라미터입니다.
So we might use training and validation sets
그래서 우리는 훈련 세트와 검증 세트를 사용해
to set what is the optimal lambda here as well.
이 lambda의 최적 값을 설정할 수 있습니다.
But the basic idea is we can set this
기본 아이디어는 이 값을 0과 무한대
to a floating point between, I guess, 0
사이의 부동 소수점으로 설정할 수
and infinity, where 0 would be basically,
있다는 겁니다. 0이면 사실상 정규화가
there is no regularization, up to infinity.
전혀 없는 상태이고, 무한대까지 갈 수 있습니다.
You have a really progressively stronger regularization.
점점 더 강한 정규화를 적용하는 거죠.
So it's very much a tunable knob you
즉, 모델이 훈련 데이터에
have for determining how much you
과적합되는 것을 얼마나
want to prevent the model from fitting to your training data.
막을지 조절할 수 있는 조절기 같은 겁니다.
And I'll go through some simple examples now of regularization.
이제 정규화의 간단한 예제를 몇 가지 살펴보겠습니다.
So here we have L2 regularization,
여기 L2 정규화가 있는데,
which basically, what you do is you have your weight matrix,
기본적으로 가중치 행렬의 각 항목을
you square each of the terms in your weight matrix,
제곱한 후 모두
and then you sum them all together.
더하는 방식입니다.
That gives you your score here that you then multiply by lambda
그 합을 람다(lambda)와 곱해서
and you add to your total loss.
전체 손실에 더하는 거죠.
That's L2 regularization.
이것이 L2 정규화입니다.
L1 regularization is very similar,
L1 정규화도 매우 비슷하지만,
but instead of squaring, you're taking the absolute value.
제곱하는 대신 절댓값을 취하는 차이가 있습니다.
So in practice, there are some differences
실제로 이 두 가지 정규화
between how these two regularizations perform
방법이 모델을 훈련할 때 어떻게 다르게 작용하는지에
when you're training models.
차이가 있습니다.
So one of the things that happens with L2 regularization,
L2 정규화에서 일어나는 일 중 하나는,
because you're squaring each of the values,
각 값을 제곱하기 때문에,
when you have a really small value, it gets squared, like,
아주 작은 값이 있을 때 예를 들어 0.
say 0.001.
001 같은 값이 제곱됩니다.
You square it, it becomes even smaller.
제곱하면 값이 더 작아지죠.
So L2 regularization allows for these really small values
그래서 L2 정규화는 0에 아주 가까운 작은 값들을 허용합니다.
close to 0, because you then square them,
제곱하기 때문에 값이
so they become even smaller.
더 작아지니까요.
And so your penalty here is very low
그래서 L2에서는 이런 아주 작은 값들이 있으면
if you have these very small values with L2.
패널티가 매우 낮습니다.
Whereas L1 you're not squaring it.
반면에 L1은 값을 제곱하지 않습니다.
So it's just whatever the baseline value is.
그냥 원래 값 그대로입니다.
It's not like it's getting smaller
정규화 항을
before you're computing this regularization term.
계산하기 전에 값이 작아지지 않는다는 뜻이죠.
So in practice what this leads to is L1 regularization.
그래서 실제로는 L1 정규화에서는
You get a lot more values that are 0, actually, in your weight
가중치 행렬에서 0이거나 0에 아주
matrix or very close to 0.
가까운 값들이 훨씬 더 많이 생깁니다.
Whereas L2 you can have generally it's more
반면 L2는 값이 작지만 0은
spread out where you have values that are small but non-zero
아닌 값들이 더 넓게 퍼져 있는 경향이 있습니다.
because the penalty becomes so small.
패널티가 아주 작아지니까요.
It seems pretty clear to you why L2 prefers spread out
L2가 모든 가중치를 작고 고르게 분포시키는 이유는
weights that are all small.
꽤 명확합니다.
But why does L1 prefer sparse vectors?
그런데 왜 L1은 희소한 벡터를 선호할까요?
So I think the way to think of it is that if a value can be 0
생각해볼 방법은, 만약 어떤 값이 0이 되어도 성능이
and your performance is roughly the same,
거의 같다면, L1은 그 값을
then this would push you towards zeroing that value.
0으로 만드는 쪽으로 밀어붙인다는 겁니다.
Whereas for L2 what you might have is the value
반면 L2는 그 값이 아주
just becomes very small but non-zero because
작지만 0은 아닌 상태로 남게
of the squaring.
됩니다. 제곱 때문이죠.
So the question is, can we talk about what is
그렇다면 0 값으로 밀어붙인다는 것이
pushing towards a 0 value mean?
무슨 의미인지 이야기해볼까요?
So we're going to talk about more--
그래서 이제 이 loss 항을 어떻게 사용하는지에
how we use this loss term.
대해 더 이야기해 보겠습니다.
But the basic idea is we're trying to minimize it.
기본적인 아이디어는 이 값을 최소화하려고 한다는 겁니다.
So we're trying to minimize the loss
즉, 모델의 loss나
or minimize the error of our model.
오류를 최소화하려고 하는 거죠.
And if we have a term here, which
여기서 양수 값을 주는 항이
is giving us positive values that it's not
있다면, 그것이 모델 성능이나 데이터
affecting the model performance and the data loss,
loss에 영향을 주지
we will remove those through the optimization procedure.
않는다면 최적화 과정에서 제거할 것입니다.
It's a trade-off.
이것은 일종의 균형 조절입니다.
You're trying to optimize the joint, some
정규화 항과 데이터 loss 항의
of the regularization term, the data loss term.
합을 최적화하려고 하는 거죠.
So if your data loss isn't changing much,
만약 데이터 loss가 크게 변하지
but you're able to go lower on the regularization term,
않지만 정규화 항을 더 낮출 수 있다면, 더 최적화된
you'll get a more optimized model.
모델을 얻을 수 있습니다.
So it will be preferred based on trying
그래서 전체 항을 최소화하려는
to minimize the overall term.
관점에서 더 선호되는 모델이 됩니다.
So I think, we'll also touch later
나중에 강의에서 더 복잡한 형태의 정규화도
in the course about much more complex forms of regularization
다룰 텐데, 모두 기본적으로는 훈련 데이터에서 더
where they're all doing this basic idea of worst
잘 맞추어 테스트 데이터에서 더
on the training data to do better on the test data.
좋은 성능을 내도록 하는 아이디어입니다.
But some of them will even change the layers of your model,
그중 일부는 모델의 레이어까지 변경하기도
so they actually get pretty complicated.
해서 꽤 복잡해집니다.
This is an ongoing research area of how to regularize models.
모델을 정규화하는 방법은 계속 연구가 진행 중인 분야입니다.
There's new papers each year, so lots of stuff here.
매년 새로운 논문이 나오고 있어서 이 분야에 많은 내용이 있습니다.
We'll only cover a small subset in this course.
이번 강의에서는 그중 일부만 다룰 것입니다.
So to summarize, why do we regularize models?
요약하자면, 왜 모델을 정규화하느냐 하면,
The first is it allows us to express some sort of preference
첫째, 가중치에 대해 어떤 선호도를 표현할 수 있기
over weights.
때문입니다.
So if for some reason in our problem,
예를 들어, 문제에 따라
we think, the solution should be spread out
해답이 넓게 퍼져 있거나
or should contain a lot of sparsity,
가중치 행렬의 많은
where a lot of the values in the weight matrix are 0,
값이 0인 희소성을 가져야
we might prefer one set of regularization L2 versus L1
한다고 생각한다면, L2 정규화보다 L1 정규화를
over another.
선호할 수 있습니다.
It also can, depending on how we're regularizing,
정규화 방법에 따라 모델을 더 단순하게
make the model simpler so that it works better on test data.
만들어서 테스트 데이터에서 더 잘 작동하게 할 수도 있습니다.
So it could simplify the model if we're, say,
예를 들어, 앞서 보여드린 것처럼
heavily regularizing really high polynomial terms in our model,
모델에서 아주 높은 차수의 다항항을 강하게
for example in what I showed earlier.
정규화하면 모델을 단순화할 수 있습니다.
Something we won't touch on in too much detail
자세히 다루지는 않겠지만,
is especially L2 regularization can actually
특히 L2 정규화는 최적화
improve the optimization process,
과정을 개선할 수도
because if you imagine this squared is like a parabola.
있습니다. 왜냐하면 제곱 함수는 포물선과 같기 때문입니다.
So if you're plotting y equals x squared it's a parabola.
y = x 제곱을 그래프로 그리면 포물선이 됩니다.
And these are convex, so you get a lot of nice optimization
이 함수들은 볼록(convex) 형태라서 전역 최솟값이 존재하는
properties where there's a global minimum.
좋은 최적화 특성을 가집니다.
We won't touch on that in this course.
이 부분은 이번 강의에서 다루지 않겠습니다.
That's beyond the scope.
범위를 벗어나기 때문입니다.
But know that for certain types of optimization,
하지만 특정 최적화 유형에서는 정규화가 모델 학습을 더 빠르게
regularization actually helps train the model faster too.
하는 데 도움을 준다는 점은 알아두시기 바랍니다.
I guess I have a question for you all.
여러분께 질문이 있습니다.
And what we'll do is you'll do a 1 if it's W1 and 2,
W1이면 손가락 하나, W2이면 손가락 두 개를
with your hand if it's W2.
들어주세요.
So which of these two weights, W1, W2,
이 두 가중치 중에서 L2 정규화기가 선호할
would the L2 regularizer prefer?
가중치는 어느 쪽일까요?
So we have our input x.
입력 x가 있습니다.
When you multiply it, you do the dot product with the weights,
가중치와 내적을 하면 점수가 같아서,
you get the same score, so you get a score of 1 either way.
어느 쪽이든 점수는 1입니다.
And here's where the data loss would be the same.
데이터 손실도 동일한 상황입니다.
And we're trying to determine which of the weights
그럼 정규화기는 어느 가중치를
would our regularizer prefer.
선호할지 판단해 보세요.
So go 1 if you think it's W1 and go 2 if you think it's W2.
W1이라고 생각하면 1, W2라고 생각하면 2를 들어주세요.
All right.
좋습니다.
Lots of 2s.
2가 많이 있네요.
Yeah, it's W2 because, as you said, it's more spread out.
네, W2인 이유는 말씀하신 대로 더 퍼져 있기 때문입니다.
You're going to be squaring each of these turns so it's 1/4 you
각 항목을 제곱할 거니까 1/4를 제곱하면
square, it becomes 1/16.
1/16이 됩니다.
You sum it all together, it's 1/4 as the total regularization
모두 합치면 전체 정규화 항은 1/4이고,
term here, and then here you square it, so it's 1.
여기서는 제곱하니까 1이 됩니다.
So it's four times lower in terms of the regularization
그래서 정규화 손실 측면에서
loss.
4배 낮은 거죠.
And, as we said, the intuition is as you
그리고 말씀드렸듯이, 직관적으로는
like, more spread out weights.
더 퍼져 있는 가중치를 선호하는 겁니다.
And then here's another question,
그럼 이제 또 다른
which one would L1 prefer now?
질문인데, L1은 지금 어떤 걸 선호할까요?
So you do 1 if it's weight 1 and 2 if it's weight 2.
가중치가 1이면 1, 2면 2를 더하는 거죠.
We got a lot of 1's.
1이 많이 나왔네요.
So this one's actually a bit of a trick question.
이건 사실 약간 트릭 질문입니다.
So what L1 regularization is you sum each of the terms,
L1 정규화는 각 항목을 합산하는 거라서
so they'll both be sum to 1.
둘 다 합이 1이 됩니다.
In practice, you probably would see this one because,
실제로는 희소성을 고려해 이쪽이 더
as we said, sparsity.
많이 쓰이긴 하죠.
But in terms of a loss standpoint
하지만 손실 관점에서는
these two weights would actually be equivalent in terms of L1
이 두 가중치가 L1 기준으로는 사실상
because 1 is just the sum of these 0.25 four times,
동등합니다. 1은 0.25를 네 번 더한 값이고, 다른
and the other one is just 1.
쪽은 그냥 1이니까요.
So they're both sum to 1.
그래서 둘 다 합이 1입니다.
And so the actual regularization term is the same for these.
따라서 실제 정규화 항은 동일합니다.
Yeah, OK.
네, 알겠습니다.
So what's an example where L1 would be preferred if this
그럼 예를 들어 0.9라면
is like 0.9, for example?
L1이 선호되는 경우는 어떤 게 있을까요?
So just to recap, we have a data set of x,y pairs.
정리하자면, 우리는 x,y 쌍으로 된 데이터셋이 있습니다.
And we have some way to calculate scores
그리고 각 클래스에 대한
for each of the classes, which in our case
점수를 계산하는 방법이 있는데, 여기서는
is just a linear model.
선형 모델입니다.
You're doing a matrix multiply.
행렬 곱셈을 수행하죠.
The loss for each of the training examples in the Softmax
각 훈련 예제에 대한 Softmax 손실은,
loss, which we discussed last time,
지난
is you exponentiate each of your scores,
시간에 다뤘듯이, 점수들을 지수화하고
and then you divide by the total sum of the scores.
전체 점수 합으로 나누는 겁니다.
So you exponentiate to make them all positive.
지수화를 해서 모두 양수로 만들고,
And then you sum to get a probability distribution.
합산해서 확률 분포를 얻는 거죠.
So the final values in this all sum to 1.
그래서 최종 값들은 모두 합쳐서 1이 됩니다.
And you have a score for each class.
각 클래스에 대한 점수가 있고,
And you take the minus log of the correct label.
정답 레이블의 마이너스 로그를 취합니다.
So this is the probability of the correct label,
이게 바로 정답
which is given here.
레이블의 확률입니다.
And the full loss is you just run
전체 손실은 모든 훈련
this over each of your training examples,
예제에 대해 이걸 계산해서 Li를
calculate Li for each of those, And?
구하는 겁니다. 그리고?
Then you add your regularization term here
그 다음 모델 가중치에
depending on what is the weights of your model.
따라 정규화 항을 더합니다.
Why do we use Softmax in general?
왜 일반적으로 Softmax를 사용할까요?
So Softmax is great because what it
Softmax는 어떤 실수
does as a function is it converts any set of floating
집합도 확률 분포로 변환해서
point numbers into a probability distribution
합이 1이 되도록 해주기 때문에
where they will sum to 1.
매우 유용합니다.
And depending on the value of the score,
그리고 점수의 값에 따라, 그것은
that will translate to the relative probability
그 값의 상대적인 확률로
of that value.
변환됩니다.
So if you have a really high positive number
그래서 만약 정말 높은 양수 값이
and everything else is very low negative, you'll have nearly 1
있고 나머지는 매우 낮은 음수라면, Softmax에서는
for Softmax and 0's almost for the other values.
거의 1에 가깝고 다른 값들은 거의 0이 될 것입니다.
So it's nice because it converts any list of floating point
이것이 좋은 점은 어떤 부동 소수점 숫자 리스트도 그
numbers into a list of probabilities based
리스트의 값에 기반한
on the values of the list.
확률 리스트로 변환해 준다는 겁니다.
That's the main utility of Softmax.
이것이 Softmax의 주요 용도입니다.
So the question is that you can view the regularization we
그래서 질문은 우리가 이야기한 정규화, 즉
talked about, which is L1, L2, as a way of regularizing
L1, L2를 가중치 크기에 기반한 정규화 방법으로
based on the magnitude of the weights, which is true.
볼 수 있다는 점인데, 이는 맞습니다.
And how does that translate to simpler models?
그것이 어떻게 더 단순한 모델로 이어질까요?
So I think in L1s explanation is actually pretty simple,
L1의 설명은 사실 꽤 간단한데,
because if we prefer, say, terms that have a lot of zeros in it,
예를 들어 0이 많은 항들을 선호한다면, 이는 기본적으로 계수가
it's basically, a linear model with fewer coefficients.
적은 선형 모델이라는 겁니다.
So that one is actually, I think,
그래서 이것은 사실 상대적으로
relatively straightforward.
직관적입니다.
But I think in general, a regularization
하지만 일반적으로 정규화가
is not always going to give you a simpler model.
항상 더 단순한 모델을 만들어 주는 것은 아닙니다.
It depends on how it's used.
그것이 어떻게 사용되느냐에 달려 있습니다.
So for example, in the diagram we showed at the very beginning
예를 들어, 여기 처음에 보여준
here, here you could imagine that you have L2 regularization
도표에서, 함수의 고차 다항항에 더 큰 페널티를
or L1 regularization where you're penalizing more
주는 L2 또는 L1
the higher degree polynomial terms of your function.
정규화를 상상할 수 있습니다.
So in that sense, it's pretty clear
그런 의미에서, 정규화를
how you could design regularization
설계해 더 단순한 모델을 선호하도록
to prefer a simpler model.
하는 것은 꽤 명확합니다.
But it doesn't always need to be that way.
하지만 항상 그렇게 될 필요는 없습니다.
Really, what it is this idea of doing worse on the training
실제로는 훈련 데이터에서 성능을 일부 희생해 테스트 데이터에서
data to do better on the test data,
더 좋은 성능을 내는 개념이고,
and that's not always going to give you a simpler model.
이것이 항상 더 단순한 모델을 의미하지는 않습니다.
And in fact, there are many types
사실, dropout
of regularization like dropout that
같은 여러 정규화 기법은 모델을 더 복잡하게
actually make your model more complex
만들면서도 테스트 데이터에서
but give you better performance on the test data.
더 좋은 성능을 제공합니다.
Cool.
좋습니다.
So now that we've talked about how
이제 우리가 주어진
we can calculate how good a given W is based on the training
W가 훈련 데이터와 정규화 항을 기반으로 얼마나 좋은지
data and this regularization term, the question now is,
계산하는 방법에 대해 이야기했으니, 다음 질문은 실제로
how do we actually find the best W?
최적의 W를 어떻게 찾느냐는 것입니다.
And this is what optimization is,
이것이 바로 최적화이며,
which is the second half of today's lecture.
오늘 강의의 후반부 내용입니다.
So I think when people describe optimization,
사람들이 최적화를 설명할 때 보통 손실 지형(loss
they will usually use this idea of a loss landscape, which
landscape)이라는 개념을 사용하는데,
you can think of as a normal landscape,
이는 지구상의 일반적인
like on planet Earth, where the up and down vertical or z-axis
지형처럼 생각할 수 있습니다. 여기서 수직 방향, 즉
direction is the loss.
z축 방향이 손실 값입니다.
So this is the value you're trying to minimize.
이 손실 값이 바로 우리가 최소화하려는 값입니다.
And then, say, in this example, you
그리고 예를 들어, 이
have two parameters in your model,
예제에서는 모델에 두 개의 파라미터가
which is the x and y direction of where
있는데, 그것은 이 지형에서 당신이
you are in this landscape.
있는 x와 y 방향입니다.
And the idea is you're just, basically, a person.
그리고 기본적으로 당신은 그냥 사람인 거죠.
You're walking around this landscape
이 지형을 걸어
and you're trying to find what is the smallest or lowest point
다니면서 가장 낮거나 최저 지점을
in the landscape.
찾으려고 하는 겁니다.
I think one of the reasons this analogy--
이 비유가 조금 약간 어긋나는
and this is a very commonly used analogy--
이유 중 하나는—이 비유가 매우
a little bit falls apart is because as humans, we can just
흔히 사용되지만—사람은 시각적으로 멀리
see, visually we can look into the distance
볼 수 있어서 계곡의 가장
and see what is the lowest point of the valley.
낮은 지점을 볼 수 있기 때문입니다.
But I think this analogy is actually pretty accurate
하지만 이 비유는 사실 사람이 눈가리개를
if you think of the person as being blindfolded.
하고 있다고 생각하면 꽤 정확하다고 봅니다.
They don't have access to any visual information.
그들은 어떤 시각 정보도 얻을 수 없습니다.
They can only feel the Earth where they are right now
지금 서 있는 지점의 땅을 만져보고
and understand what is the slope of the ground
그 지점의 경사가 어떤지
on the current point in which they're standing.
이해할 수 있을 뿐입니다.
I think if you view it in that lens,
그런 관점에서 보면
this analogy actually becomes extremely accurate for how we're
이 비유가 우리가 최적의 모델을 찾으려는 방식에 대해
trying to find the best model.
매우 정확해집니다.
And we have this complex landscape of different loss
그리고 우리는 모델의 파라미터에 따라 달라지는
values depending on the parameters of our model, which
다양한 손실 값들의 복잡한 지형을
translate to the location of the person in this landscape.
가지고 있는데, 이 지형에서 사람의 위치가 바로 파라미터에 해당합니다.
So how can you find the best point?
그럼 어떻게 최적의 지점을 찾을 수 있을까요?
We could go with a really simple idea, which is maybe a really
정말 단순한 아이디어를 생각해볼 수 있는데, 아마 별로 좋은 방법은 아니지만
bad idea, but it could work.
작동할 수도 있습니다.
So here it's just basically, a for loop where we're trying
여기서는 기본적으로 1,000개의 W
1,000 different values of W randomly,
값을 무작위로 시도하는 for 루프를 돌면서
and we're just choosing the best one.
가장 좋은 값을 선택하는 겁니다.
So obviously, not very mathematically rigorous,
분명히 수학적으로 엄밀하지는 않지만,
but you will do better than a random baseline.
무작위 기준보다는 더 잘할 수 있습니다.
And if you had nothing else to go for, maybe this isn't so bad.
다른 방법이 없다면, 이 정도도 나쁘지 않을 수 있습니다.
You would get 15.5% accuracy on the CIFAR-10 data set, which
앞서 보여드린 개구리, 자동차 등 10가지 카테고리가 있는
is the one I showed earlier with the frog and the car and things
CIFAR-10 데이터셋에서 15.
like that, with the 10 different categories.
5% 정확도를 얻을 수 있습니다.
But it doesn't perform very good.
하지만 성능이 아주 좋지는 않습니다.
I mean, the state of the on this data
이 데이터셋의
set-- it's basically solved through modern deep learning,
최신 상태는 현대 딥러닝으로 거의
and you get 99.7% accuracy.
해결되어 99.7% 정확도를 얻습니다.
So clearly, it's not bad, but it's also, I wouldn't say,
그래서 분명 나쁘지는 않지만, 특별히
particularly good.
좋다고도 할 수 없습니다.
Strategy number 2, which is what I maybe explained a bit earlier,
두 번째 전략은 아마 조금 전에 설명한 경사를
is this idea of following the slope.
따라가는 아이디어입니다.
So for this, you can imagine you're blindfolded
이 경우, 여러분은 눈가리개를 하고 손실 지형 위에 있다고
on the lost landscape, and you're feeling
상상할 수 있습니다. 발밑의
the ground underneath you.
땅을 느끼는 거죠.
And you're thinking, OK, which way
그리고 생각합니다. '어느 방향이 지형의
is the slope of the Earth pointing me?
경사면이 나를 가리키는가?' 하고요.
And I should walk in that direction at all times.
항상 그 방향으로 걸어야 합니다.
This basic idea is the fundamental way
이 기본 아이디어는 이 강의에서
in which we train all the models in this course
다루는 모든 모델, 그리고
and in which basically all deep learning models are
기본적으로 모든 딥러닝 모델을
trained, where you're feeling the location
훈련하는 방법입니다. 현재 위치의
of the current place in the loss landscape
손실 지형을 느끼면서
and you're going down the hill.
경사를 따라 내려가는 거죠.
So this is a very intuitive way to explain it.
이것이 매우 직관적인 설명입니다.
We'll now go over more of the math behind it,
이제 그 뒤에 있는 수학을 좀 더
but this is what you should be visualizing in your head.
살펴보겠지만, 머릿속에 이렇게 그려야 합니다.
So how do you actually follow the slope?
그럼 실제로 경사를 어떻게 따라가나요?
So in one dimension, I'm sure you all
1차원에서는 미분 개념에
are familiar with the idea of a derivative, which in calculus we
익숙하실 겁니다. 미적분에서 아주
can think of as this limit h definition where we add
작은 수 h를 현재 위치에 더하고, 그
a very small number to our current location,
위치에서 함수 값을 계산한 뒤,
we calculate the value of the function at that new location,
현재 위치의 함수 값을 빼고,
we subtract the current location,
그 차이를 h로 나누는
and then we divide by the step size.
극한 정의입니다.
And as we take the limit for h to approaching 0,
그리고 h가 0에 가까워질
this gives us the derivative of the function at that point.
때 이 값이 그 점에서 함수의 미분값이 됩니다.
Now, this is for 1D, but in multiple dimensions you use
이것은 1차원에 대한 것이지만,
the gradient, which is where you're calculating, essentially,
다차원에서는 gradient를 사용합니다.
this limit definition for each of the values separately.
gradient는 각 값에 대해 이 극한 정의를 따로 계산하는 것입니다.
So you have a different derivative
그래서 각 값마다
for each of your values.
다른 미분값을 갖게 됩니다.
And you get a vector instead.
그리고 벡터를 얻게 되죠.
And this gives you the direction along each dimension.
이 벡터는 각 차원에 따른 방향을 알려줍니다.
So you can actually calculate the slope in the dimension
그래서 gradient와 방향
by taking the dot product of the gradient with the direction
벡터의 내적을 취하면 그 차원에서의 기울기를 계산할
and specifically the direction of the steepest descent
수 있습니다. 특히 가장 가파른 하강
or down the hill is the negative gradient.
방향은 음의 gradient입니다.
So the gradient points up the hill.
gradient는 언덕 위를 가리키고,
The negative gradient points down the hill.
음의 gradient는 언덕 아래를 가리킵니다.
So this is the direction we should
그래서 우리가 이
be traveling if we're trying to get to the bottom of this lost
손실 함수의 최저점에 도달하려면
landscape.
이 방향으로 가야 합니다.
So maybe what are some ways you can calculate the derivative.
그럼 미분을 계산하는 방법에는 어떤 것들이 있을까요?
A really simple one is you could just actually try
아주 간단한 방법은 극한 h
to use the limit h definition with a very small h,
정의를 아주 작은 h 값으로 실제로 사용하는
so you add 0.0001.
것입니다. 예를 들어 0.0001을 더하는 거죠.
You actually can compute the last two digits
손실 함수 값이 아주 조금 변하는 것을 실제로
of the loss changed slightly.
계산할 수 있습니다.
So you can compute the difference,
그래서 차이를 계산하고,
divide by the step size, and you can get an approximation
그걸 스텝 크기로 나누면 미분값의 근사치를
of your derivative here.
얻을 수 있습니다.
And you could actually do this for each of your values
이 방법을 W의 각 값에 대해
in your W. You just do this procedure over and over again.
실제로 적용할 수 있습니다. 이 절차를 계속 반복하는 거죠.
But it has a few problems.
하지만 몇 가지 문제가 있습니다.
It's very slow because you just need
각 값을 모두 반복해야
to loop through each of the values.
하므로 매우 느립니다.
It's also approximate, so you're not even calculating
이것도 근사값이기 때문에 실제 미분값을 계산하는
the actual derivative.
것은 아닙니다.
And especially, with floating point arithmetic
특히 부동소수점 연산에서는
you can get pretty significant errors here,
상당한 오차가 발생할 수 있어서, 이
so this is not really preferred.
방법은 선호되지 않습니다.
But this basic idea or intuition of what we could be doing
하지만 우리가 할 수 있는 기본적인 아이디어나
is to calculate the derivative this way.
직관은 이렇게 미분을 계산하는 것입니다.
But really we have the loss as a function of W.
하지만 실제로는 손실 함수가 W의 함수입니다.
So we know how to calculate the scores to get
그래서 우리는 모델 함수로부터 점수를
our loss, which is given by our function for our model.
계산해서 손실을 구하는 방법을 알고 있습니다.
And we can then compute the total loss
그리고 정규화 항을 포함한
with the regularization terms as well.
전체 손실도 계산할 수 있습니다.
And this entire loss is a function of basically W's--
이 전체 손실은 기본적으로 W, Xi,
the W's, the Xi's and the yi's.
yi의 함수입니다.
So you have your W matrix, you have
즉, W 행렬과 Xi,
your Xi's and yi's, and then you have this formula with maybe
yi가 있고, 로그나 지수 함수가 포함된
some logs and exponents.
수식이 있습니다.
But fundamentally, this is a function of W, X, and y.
근본적으로 이것은 W, X, y의 함수입니다.
And we specifically want to calculate the gradient, which
그리고 우리는 특히 손실 함수에 대한 가중치의
is given by this Greek letter nabla of our loss
기울기, 즉 그리스 문자 nabla로
with respect to the weights.
표현된 기울기를 계산하고자 합니다.
So we can imagine our Xi and yi's are held constant.
Xi와 yi는 고정되어 있다고 가정할 수 있습니다.
And we're trying to calculate the derivative just
그리고 가중치에 대해서만
with respect to the weights.
미분을 계산하려고 합니다.
So to do this, we can just use calculus, use the chain rule,
이를 위해 미적분학, 연쇄법칙,
use the different methods we've learned
복잡하거나
for calculating derivatives based on complex equations
덜 복잡한 방정식의 미분 방법을 사용할 수
or not so complex.
있습니다.
But you need to have some logs and exponents and chain rules
여기에는 로그, 지수,
here to solve it.
연쇄법칙이 필요합니다.
So this will be an exercise in the homework.
이것은 숙제 문제로 나올 것입니다.
So I won't go through step by step how to do it now.
그래서 지금 단계별로 설명하지는 않겠습니다.
But it is relatively straightforward.
하지만 개념적으로 여러분 모두 이해할 수 있을 거라 생각합니다.
I think conceptually it should make sense to you all how
X와 y가 고정되어 있다고
you do this.
가정합니다.
You assume that X and the y's are constant.
그다음 W가 변할 때 미분값을 구합니다.
Then you solve for what is the derivative as you change W.
이제 우리는 데이터와 현재 W, 그리고 손실 함수에 따라 W의 기울기 dW를 계산할 수 있는 방법이 있습니다.
So now we actually have a way where we
요약하자면
can calculate W based on our--
이
sorry, dW, the gradient of W, with respect
렇
to our data and the current W, and whatever our loss function
습니다.
So this is, I guess, a summary.
수치적 기울기를 사용할 수 있지만 근사값이고 느립니다.
So you could do a numerical gradient,
장점은 코드를 작성하기 매우
but it's approximate slow.
쉽다는 점입니다.
And the nice thing is that it's very easy to write.
아주 작은 h를 더하고 차이를 h로 나누면 됩니다.
You just add a really small h, take the difference divide by h.
해석적 기울기는 정확하고 빠릅니다.
The analytic gradient is nice because it's exact.
하지만 만약 새로운 코드를 처음부터 작성한다면 오류가 있을 수 있습니다.
It's fast, but you could--
그래서 보통은 기울기
potentially, if you're creating a new gradient from scratch,
검사를 하는데, 아주 작은 h 값을 사용한
like new code to calculate it from scratch,
수치적 방법과 비교해서
you could have an error in it.
비슷한지 확인합니다.
So if you are doing this, people normally
이것은
will have a gradient check, which
코드에 버그가
is where they try the h version, where they have a really small h
없는지 확인하는
value, and then they make sure that it's
좋은
around the same neighborhood.
방법입니다.
And that's a good way to make sure you don't
여러분 숙제에도 구현이 올바른지
have any bugs in your code.
확인하는 기울기 검사가 포함될 것입니다.
There'll be gradient checks in your homework assignments
네, 질문은 우리가 보통 미분 가능한 손실 함수를
to make sure your implementations are correct
원한다고 하는데, 그래야 기울기를 계산할
also.
수 있기 때문입니다.
Yeah, so the question is we often
만약 더 좋은 손실
say we want a loss function that's differentiable
함수가 있는데 해석적으로
because then we can calculate the gradients,
기울기를
but if we have a better loss function somehow
계산할 수 없고, 대신
and we can't analytically calculate the gradient,
이 작은 h를 이용한 수치적
but we could use this h numerical method,
방법을 쓸 수 있다면, 그게
could we do that?
가능할까요?
I think, in general, it's hard to construct a better loss
일반적으로는 비미분 가능하면서
function that would be non-differentiable.
더 좋은 손실 함수를 만드는 것은 어렵다고 생각합니다.
You could possibly, though.
그럴 수도 있습니다.
There is just a true loss function
당신의 경우에 가장 좋은 진짜
that is the best for your case but it is not differentiable.
손실 함수가 있지만, 그것은 미분 가능하지 않습니다.
You could go with this approach, and it may work.
이 방법을 사용할 수 있고, 작동할 수도 있습니다.
I think, it would struggle if, for example,
예를 들어, 손실 함수가 모든
your loss is just truly non-differentiable across
지점에서 진짜로 미분 불가능하고, 기본적으로
all points, and it's basically like a cluster
연결되지 않은 점들의
of non-connected points, then moving in the steepest descent
집합이라면, 가장 가파른 하강법으로 이동하는 것이 반드시 최적의 해에 도달하지
wouldn't really get you necessarily
못할 것입니다. 왜냐하면
at your best solution if they're not well connected
점들이 잘 연결되어 지형을
and forming this geography.
형성하지 않기 때문입니다.
So it could work.
그래서 작동할 수도 있습니다.
But I would think that if your loss is not
하지만 손실 함수가 대부분
differentiable across most of the domain then
영역에서 미분 불가능하다면,
probably you wouldn't be able to use these approaches to find
아마도 이런 방법들로 최저점을 찾는
the bottom point.
것은 어려울 것입니다.
Yeah, so I guess TLDR of the explanation
설명의 요약은, 함수가
is that if your function is convex,
볼록(convex)하다면 이
then it works very well with this gradient descent
그래디언트 하강법이나 가장 가파른 하강법이 매우 잘
or steepest descent type of approach.
작동한다는 겁니다.
But if you have a non-differentiable, non-convex
하지만 미분 불가능하고 비볼록 함수라면,
function, probably this approach won't
이 방법이 잘 작동하지 않을
work as well because you're not going to be stepping
가능성이 큽니다. 왜냐하면 올바른 방향으로
in the right direction.
이동하지 않을 테니까요.
It's not necessarily error prone if your code is perfectly good,
코드가 완벽하다면 반드시 오류가 발생하는 것은 아니지만,
but maybe you have a mistake in your code
코드에 실수가 있을 수도 있고
and it's hard to tell right away.
바로 알기 어려울 수 있습니다.
But the h, the limit h definition
하지만 h, 즉 극한 h 정의는 코딩하기
is very easy to code up.
매우 쉽습니다.
You just set h to be a very small value,
h를 아주 작은 값으로 설정하고,
you run it through your function,
함수를 실행한 뒤 아주
and you add a very small amount.
작은 값을 더하면 됩니다.
So that's less error-prone for implementation.
그래서 구현 시 오류 가능성이 적습니다.
[INAUDIBLE]
[잘 들리지 않음]
For implementation.
구현 시.
OK.
네.
Not more error prone if it's worth it.
그럴 가치가 있다면 더 오류가 발생하지 않습니다.
Correct.
맞습니다.
OK.
좋습니다.
So now I'll talk about this fundamental algorithm
이제 최적화를 위한 기본 알고리즘인 gradient
for optimization called gradient descent.
descent에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
And the basic intuition is what we already explained before.
기본적인 직관은 우리가 이미 설명한 내용과 같습니다.
We calculate the slope at each point when
우리는 loss landscape
we're on our loss landscape, and we
위의 각 지점에서 기울기를
take a step in the direction downwards towards the bottom
계산하고, loss landscape의 바닥을 향해 아래
of the loss landscape.
방향으로 한 걸음 내딛습니다.
So what we do is we calculate the gradients
즉, loss 함수, 데이터, 그리고
of our weights given the loss function, the data,
현재 가중치 값을 기준으로 가중치의 기울기를
and our current weight values.
계산합니다.
This tells us how much we should change each of the weights
이것은 각 가중치를 얼마나 변경해야 경사를 따라 내려갈 수 있는지
to go down the slope, and then we have to have a step size.
알려줍니다. 그리고 우리는 한 걸음의 크기, 즉 step size가 필요합니다.
So how far down the hill are we taking a step in the direction?
얼마나 멀리 경사면을 따라 내려갈지를 결정하는 거죠.
And so you go down the hill, so it's
그래서 경사면을 따라 내려가므로
the minus sign here in the step size times the gradient.
step size에 기울기를 곱한 값에 마이너스 부호가 붙습니다.
So this is basically what gradient descent is.
이것이 기본적으로 gradient descent입니다.
You're calculating the gradient at each step.
각 단계에서 기울기를 계산하고,
And you're moving a fixed direction
음의 기울기 방향, 즉
in the direction of the negative gradient, down the hill.
경사면 아래 방향으로 고정된 크기만큼 이동하는 겁니다.
So given a concrete example here.
구체적인 예를 들어보겠습니다.
So instead of this being a 3D loss landscape,
3D loss landscape
often people will visualize it like this where we're looking
대신, 사람들이 종종 이렇게 위에서 내려다보는
down at the landscape.
식으로 시각화합니다.
And purple would represent the highest points
보라색은 가장 높은 지점을,
and red would represent the bottom or the valley here.
빨간색은 바닥이나 계곡을 나타냅니다.
And we could imagine we have our original W.
그리고 원래의 W가 있다고 상상할 수 있습니다.
We can calculate the loss.
우리는 loss를 계산할 수 있습니다.
We know the direction of the slope, the negative gradient
우리는 기울기의 방향, 즉 음의 그래디언트 방향을
direction.
알고 있습니다.
And this arrow might represent the fixed step size
그리고 이 화살표는 이전에 이야기한 고정된 스텝 크기를
that we talked about before.
나타낼 수 있습니다.
We're taking a fixed step size in that direction.
우리는 그 방향으로 고정된 스텝 크기만큼 이동하고 있습니다.
Yes, you can see it's fixed step size.
네, 고정된 스텝 크기인 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
But as the gradient becomes smaller,
하지만 그래디언트가 작아질수록 여전히 이 고정된
we're still multiplying it by this fixed step size.
스텝 크기로 곱하고 있습니다.
So the effective step size actually
그래서 실제로 효과적인
does become smaller because the gradient is smaller
스텝 크기는 그래디언트가 평평한
near the end where it's flat, or near the end
끝부분 근처에서 작아지기 때문에
where it's more flat.
작아집니다.
So this is what it looks like when
이것이 우리가 항상 가장
we're always heading in the direction
가파른 하강 방향으로
of the steepest descent.
이동할 때의 모습입니다.
So the question is, when we step down,
그렇다면, 내려갈 때 언제
how we know when we're going to stop?
멈출지 어떻게 알 수 있을까요?
Well, I guess in this formula you just keep looping forever
음, 이 공식에서는 그냥 무한히 반복해서 멈추지
so you never stop.
않는 것 같네요.
So this was probably not the best.
그래서 이 방법은 아마 최선은 아니었을 겁니다.
Normally, you have a predetermined number
보통은 미리 정해진
of iterations that you run it for.
반복 횟수만큼 실행합니다.
Or you can look at if the loss is not significantly changing
또는 손실이 고정된 양만큼 크게 변하지 않는지를
by a fixed amount also.
확인할 수도 있습니다.
You can have a tolerance for how much you're expecting the loss
손실이 계속 감소할 것으로 기대하는 허용 오차를 설정할
to keep decreasing by.
수 있습니다.
And if it's no longer decreasing--
만약 더 이상 감소하지
it's only decreasing by 1E minus 5 or 1E minus 9,
않고 1E-5나 1E-9 정도만 감소한다면, 충분히 좋은
maybe you stop there because it's good enough.
상태이므로 멈출 수 있습니다.
So those are the two ways you can determine when to stop
그래서 멈추는 방법은
is fixed number of iterations or stopping criteria of how much--
고정된 반복 횟수이거나 더 이상 크게 개선되지
we're not really improving that much anymore.
않는다는 기준입니다.
So now I'll talk about the most popular variant
이제 가장 인기 있는 그래디언트 하강법
of gradient descent, which is called stochastic gradient
변형인 확률적 그래디언트 하강법에
descent.
대해 이야기하겠습니다.
And when we talked about gradient descent
이전에 그래디언트
before, we talked about calculating
하강법을 이야기할 때,
the loss of our weights by summing over our entire training
전체 훈련 세트에 대해 각 i에 대한
set, the loss of Li for each i in our entire n training sets.
손실 Li를 모두 합산하여 가중치의 손실을 계산한다고 했습니다.
But this is potentially a lot of computation
하지만 데이터 세트가 매우 크면
if we have a very large data set.
계산량이 많아질 수 있습니다.
So what stochastic gradient descent is, is basically,
그래서 확률적 그래디언트 하강법은 전체 데이터
now instead of looking at the entire data set,
세트 대신 매번 일부
we're looking at a subset each time, which
데이터만 보는 방법입니다. 이를
we call a mini batch or a batch of data.
미니 배치 또는 배치라고 부릅니다.
And so here if we look at the code
코드를 보면 데이터
it's like we're sampling 256 data points from our data set,
세트에서 256개의 데이터를 샘플링하는데,
so the batch size is 256.
이때 배치 크기는 256입니다.
We evaluate the gradients of this 256 subset of our data set,
이 256개의 데이터 부분집합에 대해 그래디언트를 평가하고 이전과
and then we do the same thing as before.
같은 작업을 수행합니다.
So the reason why it's called stochastic gradient descent is
확률적 그래디언트 하강법이라고 부르는
because we're sampling a random subset of our data
이유는 알고리즘의 각 단계마다
set each time we're running the algorithm--
데이터 세트에서 무작위 부분집합을
each step of the algorithm.
샘플링하기 때문입니다.
So this is stochastic gradient descent.
이것이 확률적 그래디언트 하강법입니다.
You're basically running it on a random subset each time.
즉, 매번 무작위 부분집합에 대해 실행하는 것이죠.
And in practice people won't just
실제로는 완전히 무작위로
sample it completely random.
샘플링하지 않고,
They'll make sure to get through all the examples in their data
데이터 세트의 모든 예제를 한 번씩 다 보고 다시
set and then loop around again.
반복하는 방식을 사용합니다.
And that's called one epoch of training,
이것을 한 번의 에포크(epoch)라고
where you loop through all your data samples once
하며, 무작위 순서로 모든 데이터를 한
in a random order.
번 훑는 것입니다.
There are some problems with gradient descent
그래디언트 하강법이나 확률적 그래디언트 하강법에는
or stochastic gradient descent.
몇 가지 문제가 있습니다.
So this visualization is the same type
이 시각화는 이전에 보여준 컬러 버전과 같은
as the colored one I showed before where we're looking down
유형으로, 손실 지형을 위에서 내려다보는
the loss landscape.
모습입니다.
But these curves are called the level set,
하지만 이 곡선들은 레벨 셋(level
where it's a set of points where the loss is
set)이라고 불리며, 손실이 모두 같은
the same on all of them.
점들의 집합입니다.
So this is another way of visualizing--
즉, 색 없이 손실을
very popular way to visualize top-down looking at the loss,
위에서 내려다보는 매우 인기
but it's without the colors.
있는 시각화 방법입니다.
And so you could imagine that you have this phenomenon where
여기서 좁고 가파른 계곡이 있고, 그 계곡의
it's a really narrow valley, where
중앙을 따라
it's really steep along the sides,
이동하려는
and you're trying to traverse the center of the valley.
현상을 상상할 수 있습니다.
And gradient descent actually does run into issues here.
그리고 실제로 gradient descent는 여기서 문제가 발생할 수 있습니다.
Does anyone have any ideas for what could go wrong?
무엇이 잘못될 수 있을지 아이디어가 있으신가요?
Yeah, so one of the things you could do
네, 한 가지 가능한
is overshoot where you're moving up and down
문제는 이 방향을 따라 위아래로 움직일 때
along this direction.
과도하게 이동하는 것입니다.
And if it's steep enough and your step size is large enough,
만약 경사가 충분히 가파르고 스텝 크기가 크다면, 실제로
you might actually oscillate out of the valley.
계곡 밖으로 진동할 수도 있습니다.
So you can imagine if your step size is very large
스텝 크기가 매우 크고 경사가
and this is really steep, you're actually
정말 가파르다고
going to be gaining like you're moving
상상해보면, 매번 고정된
out and out each time because you always have this fixed step
스텝 크기로 계속 밖으로 나가게 되는
size.
거죠.
So if it's steep enough, you could just
그래서 경사가 충분히 가파르면 계곡 밖으로
bounce out of the valley.
튕겨 나갈 수 있습니다.
That actually does happen if your learning rate is too large.
이것은 학습률이 너무 크면 실제로 발생하는 현상입니다.
So that's one thing that can happen.
이것이 발생할 수 있는 한 가지 문제입니다.
And then also, even if you're learning rate is not too large,
그리고 학습률이 너무 크지 않고 스텝
your step size is not too large, you
크기도 적당해도, 경사가 더 가파른
can have this phenomenon where you're
방향에서 그래디언트가
sort of jittering because the gradient is much
훨씬 크기 때문에 약간
larger in the steep direction.
떨리는 현상이 있을 수 있습니다.
So you're jittering, but you're not
그래서 떨리긴 하지만
making very much meaningful progress
실제 중심을 향해 의미
towards the actual center, because you're
있는 진전은 거의 없는데,
spending all this time oscillating back and forth, up
위아래로 진동하면서 시간을 보내기
and down.
때문입니다.
So this is a pretty big issue with just default SGD.
이것은 기본적인 SGD에서 꽤 큰 문제입니다.
And then mathematically, just an aside,
그리고 수학적으로 잠깐 설명하자면, 여기서
the loss function we consider here
고려하는 손실 함수는
to have a high condition number, which
조건수가 높습니다. 조건수는
is the ratio of the largest to smallest singular
헤시안 행렬의 가장 큰 특이값과 가장 작은 특이값의
value of the Hessian matrix, which is the second derivative.
비율인데, 헤시안 행렬은 이차 미분입니다.
So you can imagine the second derivative
그래서 위아래 방향의 이차
along this up and down direction is very high.
미분은 매우 크지만,
But then side-to-side it's very low because it's very flat,
옆으로는 매우 낮아서 평평하기
so that's what causes this phenomenon.
때문에 이런 현상이 발생하는 겁니다.
All right.
좋습니다.
So one of the things we also might have an issue with SGD
또한 SGD에서 문제가 될 수 있는 것 중 하나는
is what happens if the loss function has a local minima or--
손실 함수에 국소 최소값이나, 국소 최소점 또는 새들
a local minimum or a saddle point?
포인트가 있을 때입니다.
So for example here, for just the very end of this curve
예를 들어 여기, 이 곡선의 아주 끝부분은 완전히
it's completely flat.
평평합니다.
So if we were to imagine we're moving down the hill here,
그래서 우리가 여기 언덕을 내려간다고 상상하면, 평평해서
we would just get stuck here because it's flat.
그냥 멈춰버릴 겁니다.
And we wouldn't be able to progress any further,
여기서 기울기(gradient)가
because when we take the gradient here is 0.
0이기 때문에 더 이상 진행할 수 없습니다.
So this is actually a pretty big issue
이것은 실제로 꽤 큰 문제인데, 국소
where it'll get stuck either in a local minimum
최소값(local minimum)에
because once we reach here, we don't really
갇히게 되기 때문입니다. 여기 도달하면 갈
have any direction to go.
방향이 없거든요.
The gradient is 0.
기울기가 0입니다.
Or it's very small, and we'll just
또는 기울기가 매우 작아서 여기서
oscillate back and forth here.
계속 왔다 갔다 진동할 수 있습니다.
And then here it could actually get stuck on this bottom example
그리고 여기서는 기울기가 0이라서 이 아래쪽
because the gradient is 0 here, even
예시에서 실제로 멈출 수도
though if it went a little bit further
있습니다. 조금만 더
it could go down significantly more.
가면 훨씬 더 내려갈 수 있는데도 말이죠.
Yeah, so the question is maybe we can change
그래서 질문은, 아마도 우리가 스텝을 진행하는 방식을
the way we're doing the steps.
바꿀 수 있을까요?
Maybe we could use the Hessian to determine
아마도 Hessian을 사용해서 우리가 가야 할
the direction we go.
방향을 결정할 수 있을 겁니다.
We actually do have a brief slide talking about the Hessian
사실 맨 마지막에 Hessian 방식에 대해
style approach at the very end.
간단히 설명하는 슬라이드가 있습니다.
That's not very commonly used in deep learning.
하지만 딥러닝에서는 그리 흔하게 사용되지는 않습니다.
But the short answer is yes.
하지만 짧게 대답하자면 그렇습니다.
There are going to be actually several ways in which you
사실 이걸 고려할 수 있는 여러 방법이
can account for this that we're going to go
있는데, 5분 후쯤에
into in like five minutes.
다룰 예정입니다.
So it's a good question.
좋은 질문입니다.
Yeah.
네.
We'll get to that.
곧 다룰 거예요.
So I think one of the other things that you might not know
제가 생각하기에 여러분이 잘 모를 수도 있는 다른 점
is that empirically, saddle points are actually
중 하나는, 경험적으로 고차원 모델로
much more common as you move to higher dimensional models,
갈수록 안장점(saddle points)이
so as your weight matrix gets larger and larger,
훨씬 더 흔하다는 겁니다. 즉, 가중치 행렬이 커질수록 이런
you're more likely to find these saddle points.
안장점을 만날 가능성이 높아집니다.
And there's this paper describing
이 빈도에 대해
the frequency of them.
설명하는 논문도 있습니다.
If you don't know a saddle point--
안장점이 뭔지
it's called a saddle point because it's shaped
모른다면—말 안장 모양이라서
like a saddle on a horse.
안장점이라고 부릅니다.
And at the center of this saddle,
이 안장의 중심에서는 모든
the gradient is actually 0 in all directions,
방향으로 기울기(gradient)가 0입니다.
so it's like the bottom of this and at the top
그래서 이 부분은 곡률의 바닥이자
of this carvature.
꼭대기 같은 지점입니다.
And so in both the x and the y directions the gradient is 0,
x축과 y축 방향 모두에서 기울기가 0이라서,
so you could get stuck here despite being
손실 함수의 양쪽으로 크게
very close to going significantly down the loss
내려갈 수 있는 지점에 매우 가까워도
landscape on either side.
여기서 멈출 수 있습니다.
So this is also a pretty common issue with SGD
이것은 SGD에서 꽤 흔한 문제이기도
where these saddle points and as we
합니다. 고차원
move to higher dimensional spaces,
공간, 즉 파라미터가
or this is equivalent to models with more parameters,
많은 모델로 갈수록 이런 현상이
this is more and more common.
더 자주 발생합니다.
This is a big issue.
이 문제는 매우 심각합니다.
And then a final issue with SGD is
SGD의 마지막 문제는 매번
that we are sampling a subset of our data each time.
데이터의 일부만 샘플링한다는 점입니다.
So we're not looking at the whole--
전체 데이터에 대한 손실을
this represents the entire loss across all the data.
나타내는 이 값 전체를 보지 않고,
But we're looking at just a subset each time.
매번 일부 데이터만 봅니다.
So we'll actually have somewhat noisy update steps
그래서 전체 데이터셋을 보지 않기 때문에
because we're not looking at the entire data set.
업데이트 단계에 다소 노이즈가 섞이게 됩니다.
So we'll be stepping towards the center--
우리는 여기서 도달하려는 국소 최소점(local
towards this local minimum that we're trying to reach here.
minimum) 쪽으로 나아가고 있지만,
But each step doesn't go directly in that direction.
각 단계가 정확히 그 방향으로 가지는 않습니다.
So there's some noise in how we're progressing because we're
데이터셋을 부분 샘플링하기
subsampling the data set.
때문에 진행 과정에 노이즈가 있는 거죠.
OK, cool.
좋습니다.
I think to summarize, these are the main issues.
요약하자면, 이게 주요 문제들입니다.
And there's a pretty neat trick you can do where you just
그리고 모멘텀을 추가하는 꽤 멋진
basically add momentum.
방법이 있습니다.
And you can really think of this as the same way
이것은 마치 공이 언덕을 굴러 내려가면서
as if you have a ball that's rolling down the hill
모멘텀을 얻는 것과 같은 방식으로
where it gains momentum.
생각할 수 있습니다.
It's actually very similar to how
물리적 특성 측면에서
it's modeled in terms of the physical properties.
모델링된 방식과 실제로 매우 유사합니다.
So it's a good way to gain intuition about it
그래서 적어도 직관을 얻는 데
at the very least.
좋은 방법입니다.
So you can imagine that it could help
로컬 미니멈이 있어도 충분한
whether you have these local minimum, because if you're
속도로 굴러 내려가면
rolling down with enough velocity,
빠져나올 수 있다고
you'll be able to come out of it.
상상할 수 있습니다.
If you have the saddle points or the just flat point here,
새들 포인트나 평평한 지점이 있어도 모델이 언덕 전체를
the model, it's been rolling down the entire hill,
굴러 내려왔기 때문에 여기서 더
so it won't get stuck here anymore.
이상 멈추지 않습니다.
It will continue.
계속 진행할 것입니다.
Also if you have this poor conditioning value,
조건이 좋지 않은 값이 있어도 약간의
you will still have maybe some oscillation.
진동은 있을 수 있습니다.
But the nice thing is that it will accumulate
하지만 좋은 점은 여러 단계가 계속 같은 방향으로
speed in this direction to the because it
진행되면서 이 방향으로
will have multiple steps that keep going that way.
속도가 누적된다는 겁니다.
So it will gain faster and faster towards the center here.
그래서 중심 쪽으로 점점 더 빠르게 이동하게 됩니다.
So it also helps with this problem.
이 문제에도 도움이 됩니다.
Finally, it can also help average
마지막으로, 그래디언트의
out some of the noise with the gradients
노이즈를 평균화하는 데도 도움이
because they all have a direction in common, which
됩니다. 왜냐하면 모두 공통된 방향, 즉 이 미니멈
is towards this minimum here.
쪽을 향하고 있기 때문입니다.
And so as you're computing the momentum, it builds on itself,
그래서 모멘텀을 계산할 때 스스로
and it will converge faster because the noise is accounted
누적되며, 노이즈가 모두 공유하는 방향을
for by looking at the direction they all share
반영하기
in common, which is included in the momentum.
때문에 더 빠르게 수렴합니다.
So let me show you how to actually do it,
이제 실제로 어떻게 하는지
but this is the general intuition for how
보여드리겠습니다만, 이것이
momentum works.
모멘텀 작동 원리에 대한 일반적인 직관입니다.
So we have SGD here.
여기 SGD가 있습니다.
We have our mini batch x.
미니 배치 x가 있습니다.
We're computing the gradient, which is dx.
우리는 기울기, 즉 dx를 계산하고 있습니다.
We have the learning rate or the step size, which we multiply,
학습률 또는 스텝 크기가 있는데, 이것을 곱한 후에 음수로
and then we do the negative because we
바꾸는 이유는 경사를
need to go down the hill.
내려가야 하기 때문입니다.
This gives us our new x, so this is SGD.
이것이 새로운 x를 주는데, 이것이 바로 SGD입니다.
With momentum, we're now updating by this velocity term.
모멘텀을 사용할 때는 이제 이 속도(velocity) 항으로 업데이트합니다.
So instead of updating by the gradient at the specific point,
즉, 특정 지점의 기울기로 업데이트하는
we're updating by the velocity.
대신 속도로 업데이트하는 거죠.
And the velocity at a given time step
주어진 시간 단계에서
is given by the previous velocity plus the current slope.
속도는 이전 속도에 현재 기울기를 더한 값입니다.
So this is how you calculate it.
이렇게 계산하는 겁니다.
And you have this rho value, which
그리고 rho 값이 있는데,
is the momentum, the actual how much momentum you want to have.
이것이 모멘텀, 즉 얼마나 많은 모멘텀을 가질지 결정합니다.
And if you have it very high, then your new velocity
만약 이 값이 매우 높으면, 새로운
is more dependent on the previous time step's velocity.
속도는 이전 시간 단계의 속도에 더 의존하게 됩니다.
And this is a running average of the last gradients
여기 모멘텀 항에서 지난 기울기들의 가중 평균을 구하는데,
in the momentum term here gives you how much to weight
이것이 과거와 현재를 얼마나
the past versus the present.
가중할지 결정합니다.
So now we're updating by this.
그래서 이제 우리는 이 값으로 업데이트합니다.
And we still have this alpha, which is the step size.
그리고 여전히 스텝 크기인 알파(alpha)가 있습니다.
So it's actually a very simple change.
사실 매우 간단한 변화입니다.
You just are now computing the velocity,
현재 속도와 기울기의
which is a function of the current velocity
함수인 속도를 이제 계산하는
plus our gradient.
것뿐입니다.
So I think I'll pause for questions here.
여기서 질문을 받겠습니다.
This is the explanation of momentum.
이것이 모멘텀에 대한 설명입니다.
And maybe I could also recap briefly
그리고 아마도 이 문제들을 어떻게 해결하는지 간단히
how it resolves all these issues we saw.
다시 정리할 수 있을 것 같습니다.
So if now that you're adding momentum
이제 과거의 그래디언트 단계들에
in over the past gradient steps, you
모멘텀을 더하면, 이 방향을 계속
could see how it would keep continuing along this direction.
따라가게 되는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
And depending on your rho, if your momentum is very high,
그리고 rho 값에 따라
it would keep going and be able to account for a very large
모멘텀이 매우 크면, 여기 국소 최소값의 큰
of hump here with the local minimum.
고비도 넘을 수 있습니다.
Also it's very good at these saddle points
또한 이 방법은 새들 포인트에서 매우
because it will just continue along the direction in which it
효과적인데, 이전에 가던 방향을 상당 시간
was going previously for a significant amount of time
계속 유지하기 때문입니다. 그리고 조건이
and poor conditioning.
좋지 않은 경우에도 마찬가지입니다.
If we're having cumulatively going to the right
만약 매 단계마다 누적해서
upon each step, the momentum will also be consistent there
오른쪽으로 간다면, 모멘텀도 일관되게 쌓일
and build up.
것입니다.
And then if we're oscillating significantly here,
그리고 여기서 진동이 심하면, 값들이 서로 상쇄되어
it'll move less in the direction because the values
방향으로의 이동이
will cancel out.
줄어듭니다.
In terms of the current direction and the velocity,
현재 방향과 속도는 반대 방향을
they'll be pointing the opposite direction,
가리키기 때문에
so it'll get minimized.
최소화됩니다.
So the question is, what happens if you're
그렇다면 새들 위를 계속
rolling right along the saddle?
굴러간다면 어떻게 될까요?
I mean, I think, in practice it's very unlikely.
사실 실무에서는 매우 드문 일이라고 생각합니다.
But in that case, yeah, you would just
하지만 그런 경우라면,
get stuck in the saddle, yeah.
새들에 갇히게 될 겁니다.
I think that's your initial conditions, wherever
초기 조건, 즉 어디서 시작하느냐가 매우
you start is very unfortunate.
불운한 경우라고 생각합니다.
So yeah, sometimes I guess that could happen,
그래서 가끔 그런 일이 일어날 수도 있지만,
but it's very unlikely.
가능성은 매우 낮습니다.
Yeah, and it's also why in practice people
그리고 실제로 사람들이 한
won't run a single model training run.
번의 모델 학습만 하지 않는 이유이기도 합니다.
Often they'll run multiple ones with different random seeds,
보통은 여러 번, 다른 랜덤 시드로 여러 번
just in case something like that could happen.
실행해서 그런 일이 발생할 가능성에 대비합니다.
Another thing is if you're doing stochastic gradient descent,
또한 확률적 경사 하강법을 사용하면, 적어도
you're much more likely to have, at least, a little bit of noise
약간의 노이즈가 있어서 새들에서 바로 왔다
to get you out of directly in that saddle
갔다 하는 상황에서 벗어날 가능성이 훨씬
back and forth, so I think it's basically,
높습니다. 그래서 기본적으로는 무작위성
it never would happen because of the randomness.
때문에 그런 일이 거의 일어나지 않습니다.
But hypothetically, I think that could occur.
하지만 가설적으로는 그런 일이 발생할 수도 있다고 생각합니다.
Yeah.
네.
So the question is why is the saddle just an issue with SGD
그래서 질문은 왜 saddle point 문제가 SGD에서만 발생하고 일반적인
and not optimization in general?
최적화에서는 문제가 되지 않느냐는 거죠?
It would also be an issue with the entire data set.
전체 데이터 세트에서도 문제가 될 수 있습니다.
It might even be more common
오히려 전체 데이터 세트에서 더 흔할 수도 있습니다.
So it's an issue that SGD faces, but it's also an issue
그래서 이것은 SGD가 직면하는 문제이지만,
that other optimization algorithms that just rely
추가적인 장치 없이 단순히
on gradient descent with no bells and whistles attached
gradient descent에 의존하는 다른
would also--
최적화 알고리즘들도 같은
they would face the same thing.
문제를 겪을 겁니다.
Yeah.
네.
So the question is, does adding the momentum make
그래서 질문은, momentum을 추가하면 수렴이 더
it more difficult to converge because we'll overshoot
어려워지는가, 즉 overshoot해서 다시
and then you'll have to come back?
돌아와야 하는가 하는 거죠?
I think the short answer is yeah.
짧게 말하면 네, 그렇습니다.
It might not help with converging, but it will help
수렴하는 데 도움이 되지 않을 수
you find--
있지만,
on average will help you find a better minimum point
평균적으로 더 좋은 최소점을 찾는 데는
to converge to.
도움이 됩니다.
So it will converge maybe more slowly because you won't
그래서 momentum이 없으면 국소 최소점에 갇혀서 빨리 수렴할 수 있지만, momentum이
get stuck in a local minimum.
있으면 더 천천히 수렴하더라도 더 좋은 지점에 도달할 수 있습니다.
You would just converge here if there was no momentum
만약 momentum이 없으면 여기서 그냥 수렴할 거고, momentum이
versus overshooting.
있으면 overshoot가 발생하는 거죠.
So I think a lot of this stuff is empirically shown where
이런 내용들은 경험적으로 많이 증명되었고,
it's--
특정
it happens to be with the specific class
신경망 종류에서 그런 경향이
of neural networks.
있습니다.
The momentum does help training.
momentum은 학습에 도움이 됩니다.
But this is the intuition for why we prefer it.
이게 momentum을 선호하는 직관적인 이유입니다.
I think, to be honest, people will use whatever works best.
솔직히 말하면, 사람들은 가장 잘 작동하는 방법을 사용합니다.
And there are cases where people have
어떤 경우에는
found that stochastic gradient descent without momentum
momentum 없는 SGD가 특정 모델에서
would outperform for a particular model.
더 좋은 성능을 보이기도 했습니다.
So here's the intuition about why it could perform better.
그래서 momentum이 더 잘 작동할 수 있는 이유에 대한 직관을 말씀드린 거고,
But in practice, people will just
실제로는 여러 방법을
try a bunch of different ones and see what works best.
시도해 보고 가장 잘 맞는 걸 선택합니다.
And I'm going over the most common ones that people try now.
지금 말씀드리는 건 사람들이 가장 흔히 시도하는 방법들입니다.
Yeah.
네.
But yeah, you're right.
맞아요.
It could hurt convergence, potentially.
수렴에 방해가 될 수도 있습니다.
All right.
좋습니다.
I'll continue then.
그럼 계속하겠습니다.
So yeah, I think we went through this.
네, 이 부분은 이미 다뤘다고 생각합니다.
And one other thing I wanted to point out
그리고 한 가지 더 말씀드리고 싶은
is that there are different ways you can formulate this.
건, 이걸 표현하는 방법이 여러 가지 있다는 겁니다.
So these equations are identical,
이 방정식들은
but you'll sometimes, depending on the implementation,
동일하지만, 구현에 따라 다르게 쓰이는
see it written in different ways.
경우가 있습니다.
But they're doing the same thing.
하지만 결국 같은 일을 하는 거죠.
Maybe in interest of time I'll skip over why they're identical.
시간 관계상 왜 동일한지 설명은 생략하겠습니다만,
But you could go over in the slide
슬라이드에서 직접
and prove to yourself that these are essentially
확인해 보시면 본질적으로 같은
the same formulations.
공식임을 증명할 수 있습니다.
OK.
네.
I think, the next thing I'll talk about
다음으로 이야기할 것은
is a different optimizer.
다른 옵티마이저입니다.
So we talked about momentum.
그래서 우리는 momentum에 대해 이야기했습니다.
And now we'll talk about something called RMSProp.
이제 RMSProp이라는 것에 대해 이야기할 겁니다.
So RMSProp is a bit of an older method now 2012,
RMSProp은 2012년에 나온 다소 오래된 방법인데, Geoffrey
but it came out by Geoffrey Hinton's group.
Hinton 그룹에서 나왔습니다.
And the basic idea is to, instead
기본 아이디어는 momentum이
of just having this running velocity, which
포착하는 이 달리는 속도(velocity)
the momentum captures, it's to actually add
대신에, 기울기를 원소별로
element-wise scaling of the gradient.
스케일링하는 것입니다.
So how do we do this is we have this gradient squared term.
이렇게 하는 방법은 기울기 제곱 항을 사용하는 것입니다.
And the decay rate here is very much like the momentum term
여기서 감쇠율(decay rate)은 이전에 설명한 momentum
we explained before, but now it's on the squared gradient.
항과 매우 비슷하지만, 이제는 제곱된 기울기에 적용됩니다.
So we have this running average where we take the previous term
그래서 이전 항인 기울기 제곱을 취해서 달리는
here the gradient squared.
평균을 구합니다.
And then we do 1 minus times.
그리고 1 빼기 곱하기를 합니다.
And then here it is the-- literally, the gradient squared.
여기서는 문자 그대로 기울기 제곱입니다.
And so this is a running average of our squared gradients.
이것은 제곱된 기울기의 달리는 평균입니다.
So bigger values will get much bigger,
큰 값은 훨씬 커지고, 작은
smaller values will get much smaller.
값은 훨씬 작아집니다.
And if there are consistently large gradients
특정 값에서 일관되게 큰
in certain values those will get very large
기울기가 있다면, 달리는
as we continue our running average here.
평균이 계속되면서 매우 커집니다.
And we're actually going to divide here.
그리고 실제로 여기서 나눗셈을 합니다.
In the update step we divide by the square root of it.
업데이트 단계에서 그것의 제곱근으로 나누는 겁니다.
So the basic idea here is we're actually now stepping--
기본 아이디어는 이제 우리가 실제로
someone asked earlier I think there was a question--
스텝을 밟는 방향을 바꾸는
what if we changed the direction in which we're stepping?
것에 관한 질문이 있었는데,
This is exactly the type of thing you can do.
이것이 바로 여러분이 할 수 있는 종류의 작업입니다.
And this is what this is doing where we're dividing
그리고 이것이 바로 제곱된 그래디언트
by the squared gradient term.
항으로 나누는 작업입니다.
So for values in which we have very large squared gradients,
그래디언트가 매우 큰 값들, 즉 도함수가 매우
for the values of W in which the derivative is very large,
큰 W 값들에 대해서는 더 큰 값으로
we'll divide by a larger value.
나누게 됩니다.
So we'll step not as far in that direction.
그래서 그 방향으로 한 걸음 덜 나아가게 되는 거죠.
And the more flat regions we'll step farther because we're
그리고 더 평평한 영역에서는 더 작은
dividing by a smaller term here.
값으로 나누기 때문에 더 멀리 나아가게 됩니다.
So this is the basic intuition behind it.
이것이 바로 기본적인 직관입니다.
And it very much addresses one of the questions someone
그리고 이것은 누군가가 이전에 질문했던, 우리가
had earlier about can we change the way we're
나아가는 방향을 바꿀 수 있느냐는 질문에
stepping in the direction?
아주 잘 답해줍니다.
And that's exactly what this is doing here.
바로 이것이 여기서 하는 일입니다.
So you still have a learning rate,
그래서 여전히
but you're dividing it by this square root
학습률이 있지만, 누적된 제곱
of the cumulative squared gradients,
그래디언트의 제곱근으로 나누기 때문에
which gives you larger steps in the flatter areas of your loss
손실 함수의 평평한 영역에서는 더 큰 걸음, 가파른
landscape and shorter steps in the very steep areas.
영역에서는 더 짧은 걸음을 내딛게 됩니다.
Can anyone explain, I just gave a brief summary,
누군가 설명할 수 있나요? 제가 간단히
but what happens in this specific line here of the code?
요약했는데, 이 코드의 특정 줄에서 무슨 일이 일어나는지요?
What happens with our gradient step direction?
그래디언트 스텝 방향에 무슨 일이 일어나나요?
How does it change?
어떻게 변하나요?
We're dividing by this value, which
우리는 현재 그래디언트와
is dependent on the current gradient and also
과거 그래디언트에
the past gradients.
의존하는 이 값으로 나누고 있습니다.
When these values are very large,
이 값들이 매우 클
so these are vector operations.
때, 이들은 벡터 연산입니다.
So we have a set of derivatives here.
여기 도함수 집합이 있고,
And we're dividing element-wise by another set
우리는 또 다른 제곱된 그래디언트 값
of squared gradient values.
집합으로 요소별로 나누고 있습니다.
So when it's very large, the denominator is very large,
그래서 분모가 매우 크면 분모가 매우 커지고, 그
then the step becomes effectively less
방향으로의 스텝이 사실상
in that direction because we're dividing by a large value.
작아집니다. 큰 값으로 나누기 때문입니다.
And when it's a very small value the step
그리고 값이 매우 작으면 스텝이
becomes much larger, because the gradient squared term is small.
훨씬 커집니다. 왜냐하면 그래디언트 제곱 항이 작기 때문입니다.
So it's in the denominator and we're increasing
그래서 분모에 있고, 효과적인
the effective step size.
스텝 크기를 증가시키는 겁니다.
Oh, yeah.
네, 맞습니다.
So it's specifically for this type of example
그래서 특히 여기처럼 아주 좁은
here where you have maybe a very narrow valley where
계곡이 있을 때, 더 평평한 방향으로
you want to be moving more in the flatter direction.
더 많이 움직이고 싶을 때 사용하는 겁니다.
Yes, the question is, what is a small gradient
네, 질문은 이 맥락에서 작은 그래디언트가 무엇을
mean in this context?
의미하는가 하는 거죠?
And how does this help us move up
그리고 이것이 가파른 방향으로는 덜
along the steep directions less and along the flat directions
움직이고 평평한 방향으로는 더 움직이도록 어떻게
more?
도와주는가 하는 겁니다.
Yeah, yeah.
네, 네.
So I think actually, this is maybe a great visual
사실 이게 세 가지 다른 접근법을
because it compares the three different approaches here.
비교하는 훌륭한 시각 자료인 것 같습니다.
So we have with momentum, which you
그래서 모멘텀을 사용하면, 아까 질문이
can see it overshoots as there is a question about earlier.
있었던 것처럼 과도하게 움직이는 것을 볼 수 있습니다.
But then it comes back.
하지만 다시 돌아옵니다.
You have SGD, which is slower because it's just always moving
SGD는 항상 고정된 방향으로 움직이기 때문에
in the fixed direction.
더 느립니다.
And then you have RMSProp, which we just mentioned.
그리고 방금 언급한 RMSProp이 있습니다.
So the way that RMSProp works is because the gradient
RMSProp이 작동하는 방식은, 제가
in the direction that I'm moving my mouse here
마우스를 움직이는 방향의
is higher, the gradient squared term is larger,
그래디언트가 더 크기 때문에, 그래디언트 제곱 항이 더
so we move less in that-- sorry, we move less in that direction.
커서 그 방향으로 덜 움직인다는 겁니다.
So you can see it actually quickly starts turning here
그래서 실제로 여기서 중심 쪽으로 빠르게 방향을 틀기
towards the center where it's a flatter landscape at this point,
시작하는데, 그 지점이 더 평평한 지형이고 그
but it's traversing more in that direction.
방향으로 더 많이 이동하고 있습니다.
So we're actually changing the direction we're going based on--
즉, 가파른 방향으로는 덜 가고 평평한 방향으로는
going less in the steep direction
더 가도록 방향을 실제로
and more in the flat direction.
바꾸고 있는 겁니다.
So
이렇게 세
These are the three.
가지가 있습니다.
And then there's one more we'll discuss,
그리고 하나 더 논의할
which is by far the most popular optimizer used
것이 있는데, 현대 딥러닝에서 가장
in modern deep learning.
인기 있는 옵티마이저입니다.
So it's just a combination of the SGD momentum and RMSProp.
이것은 SGD 모멘텀과 RMSProp의 조합일 뿐입니다.
So here is almost what the Adam optimizer
여기 거의 Adam 옵티마이저와 같은 것이 있는데,
is, which is the most popular optimizer in deep learning.
딥러닝에서 가장 인기 있는 옵티마이저입니다.
And you also have all the prerequisite knowledge now
그리고 이제 이를 이해할 수 있는
to understand it.
모든 사전 지식을 갖추셨습니다.
So you look at it.
한번 살펴보겠습니다.
And this first term here in the red
빨간색으로 표시된 첫
is basically the momentum we described before,
번째 항은 기본적으로 이전에
where we have the current, so the beta 1 is the momentum term,
설명한 모멘텀으로, beta 1이 모멘텀 항이고 여기서
and then we have the velocity here.
velocity가 있습니다.
And we're taking a running average.
그리고 우리는 이동 평균을 취하고 있습니다.
The second moment here is the gradient squared term
두 번째 모멘트는 RMSProp의
for RMSProp.
그래디언트 제곱 항입니다.
And we're doing the same thing here where
여기서도 학습률을 스텝 크기
we're multiplying the learning rate instead of by the step size
대신 velocity에 곱하는 같은 작업을
by the velocity.
하고 있습니다.
But now we're still doing the thing
하지만 이제도 여전히
where we take the square root.
제곱근을 취하는 작업을 하고 있습니다.
And it's the second moment here.
그리고 이것이 두 번째 모멘트입니다.
And the reason they use first moment second moment
첫 번째 모멘트와 두 번째
is like a relation to physics and mechanics,
모멘트를 사용하는 이유는 물리학과 역학과의
but it's basically just a combination of the two things
연관성 때문인데, 기본적으로는 앞서
we explained earlier, where you're accelerating movement
설명한 두 가지를 결합한 것으로, 평탄한 방향에서는
along the flat directions, dampening it
가속을 하고 가파른
along the steep ones, and you're also
방향에서는 감쇠하며, 모멘텀과
adding this notion of momentum and velocity.
속도의 개념을 추가하는 것입니다.
So you gradually build up speed if you're continuously
그래서 같은 방향으로 계속
moving in the same direction.
움직이면 점차 속도가 붙습니다.
So as it's written right now, this
지금 적힌 대로라면, 실제로 첫
will actually run into issues at the very first time step.
번째 시간 단계에서 문제가 발생할 수 있습니다.
And it might be a little bit unclear to you why,
왜 그런지 조금 불분명할 수도 있는데, 누군가
but I'll actually wait for someone to have a guess.
추측해 보길 기다리겠습니다.
So one thing to note is that these betas, beta1 beta2,
한 가지 주목할 점은 이 베타들, beta1과
are usually initialized very close to 1, so 0.9, 0.999,
beta2가 보통 1에 아주 가깝게 초기화된다는 겁니다, 예를 들어 0.9, 0.
and that these two values are also initialized to 0.
999이고, 이 두 값도 0으로 초기화된다는 점입니다.
So during your first time step, if you just
그래서 첫 번째 시간 단계에서 Adam의
use this formulation of Adam you would
이 공식을 그대로
run into potentially unwanted behavior.
사용하면 원하지 않는 동작이 발생할 수 있습니다.
So one of the other things is it has to do with the second moment
또 다른 문제 중 하나는 두 번째 모멘트 계산과
calculation.
관련이 있습니다.
So this is the main issue here.
여기가 주요 문제입니다.
When you calculate the second moment
두 번째 모멘트를
and then use it on the next line, you run into an issue.
계산하고 다음 줄에서 사용하면 문제가 발생합니다.
Yeah, so the denominator is 0, basically.
네, 분모가 기본적으로 0이라는 겁니다.
Yeah, that's the exact issue.
네, 그게 바로 문제의 핵심입니다.
So it starts at 0, so this term is 0.
처음에 0에서 시작하니까 이 항이 0이 됩니다.
You have a very large beta.
베타 값이 매우 큽니다.
So this value is very small.
그래서 이 값은 매우 작아집니다.
And if your gradient is not very large in your first step
그리고 첫 번째 단계에서 그래디언트가 크지
you can have this whole term basically be very close to 0.
않으면 이 전체 항이 거의 0에 가까워질 수 있습니다.
Now, we're dividing by something very close to 0,
이제 거의 0에 가까운 값으로 나누게
and it just creates a very large initial step,
되니, 그래디언트가 작았음에도 불구하고 매우
even though our gradient was small.
큰 초기 스텝이 만들어집니다.
So that's probably not something we really want.
이건 아마 우리가 원하지 않는 상황일 겁니다.
And so the final thing that Adam has is it
그래서 Adam이 마지막으로 하는 것은 여기
adds these bias terms here, which is specifically
편향 보정(bias terms)을 추가하는
to account for this issue where it's dependent now
건데, 이는 훈련 시간 단계에 의존하는
on the time step of training.
이 문제를 해결하기 위한 것입니다.
So I think, this is also something
이 부분은 숙제에서도 다룰
you'll go into in the homework.
거라고 생각합니다.
I just want to give the basic intuition
저는 단순 구현이 왜 작동하지 않는지,
behind Adam why the naive implementation wouldn't work,
즉 너무 큰 초기 스텝이 생기는 이유에 대한
which is this really large initial step.
기본 직관만 설명하고 싶었습니다.
And you'll go over in the homework implementing this.
그리고 숙제에서 이것을 구현해 보실 겁니다.
And you'll see how the time step is used.
그리고 시간 단계가 어떻게 사용되는지 보실 수 있습니다.
But the basic idea this is to account for that very large
하지만 기본 아이디어는 아주 큰 초기 단계를
initial step.
보정하는 것입니다.
And as your time step increases, these bias terms
시간 단계가 커질수록 이런 바이어스
are not needed as much.
항은 덜 필요해집니다.
OK, cool.
좋습니다.
These are some good defaults that people normally use.
이것들은 보통 사람들이 사용하는 좋은 기본값들입니다.
If you're training a model with Adam, you go with these,
Adam으로 모델을 훈련할 때 이 값을 사용하면, 잘 될
and maybe it'll work, maybe it won't.
수도 있고 아닐 수도 있습니다.
But it's a good starting point.
하지만 좋은 출발점입니다.
And you can then tell from the remaining slides,
그리고 남은 슬라이드에서 학습률이 적절한지
we'll talk about how do you know if your learning rates right.
어떻게 아는지 이야기할 겁니다.
How do you know if these other values are right.
다른 값들이 적절한지 어떻게 아는지도요.
So I'll speed up a little bit just in the interest of time.
시간 관계상 조금 속도를 내겠습니다.
But the basic idea is that you can
하지만 기본 아이디어는 다양한
see all these different optimizers converging.
옵티마이저들이 수렴하는 모습을 볼 수 있다는 겁니다.
They all have different properties.
각각 다른 특성을 가지고 있습니다.
You can see how Adam is this combination of RMSProp and SGD
Adam이 RMSProp과 모멘텀을 가진 SGD의 조합이라는 것을
with momentum, where it has characteristics of both, which
시각적으로 볼 수 있는데, 두 가지 특성을
is very neat to see visually.
모두 가진다는 점이 매우 흥미롭습니다.
It aligns with our intuition.
이것은 우리의 직관과도 일치합니다.
One final topic related to Adam is
Adam과 관련된 마지막 주제는
that we could look at how regularization
정규화가 옵티마이저와 어떻게 상호작용하는지
interacts with optimizer.
살펴보는 것입니다.
So for example, if we have L2 regularization,
예를 들어, L2 정규화가 있다면, 이것이
how does this affect how the optimizer works?
옵티마이저 작동 방식에 어떤 영향을 미칠까요?
And I think the answer is it's actually not
사실 답은 바로 명확하지
immediately obvious.
않습니다.
And you can do it in different ways.
그리고 여러 가지 방법으로 할 수 있습니다.
So in default Adam, they compute L2 when they're
기본 Adam에서는 그라디언트를 계산할 때 L2를
computing their gradient.
함께 계산합니다.
So we looked at the gradient and there was
그래서 그라디언트를 보면, 손실 부분이
the loss portion of our-- so the data loss portion and then
있었죠—데이터 손실 부분과 정규화 손실
the regularization loss.
부분이 있었습니다.
For Adam, it's using both of those
Adam은 그라디언트를 계산할
when it computes the gradient.
때 이 두 가지를 모두 사용합니다.
But AdamW basically, only looks at the data loss
하지만 AdamW는 기본적으로 모멘트
for doing all of these moment calculations and all
계산과 모든 단계에서 데이터
these steps, and it just adds the regularization term
손실만 보고, 정규화 항은
at the end here.
마지막에 더합니다.
So basically, all I'm trying to describe to you
즉, 제가 말씀드리고 싶은
all is there is flexibility for how
것은 정규화를 옵티마이저에
you incorporate regularization into your optimizers.
포함하는 방법에 유연성이 있다는 겁니다.
Weight decay is generally when you just
Weight decay는
add it at the end, L2 regularization at the end,
보통 마지막에 L2
and you don't include it in the actual optimizer
정규화를 더하는 방식이고, 실제로
for how you're calculating the velocities
속도나 모멘텀 계산에는
and momentums, et cetera.
포함하지 않습니다.
So this is the main difference.
이것이 주요 차이점입니다.
And sometimes under a lot of settings,
그리고 많은 경우에 AdamW가 조금 더 잘 작동하는
AdamW works slightly better.
경우가 있습니다.
I think the Llama series from Meta they all use AdamW,
Meta의 Llama 시리즈도 모두 AdamW를 사용하는데, 아마도
I assume because it does slightly better for them.
조금 더 성능이 좋아서 그런 것 같습니다.
So we have one function optimizer.
우리는 하나의 함수인 optimizer를 가지고 있습니다.
Why are you splitting it into two?
왜 두 개로 나누는 걸까요?
Yeah, so if you mix it into one function, that's what Adam does.
네, 하나로 합치면 그게 Adam입니다.
And AdamW is specifically, separating it into two.
AdamW는 특별히 두 개로 분리하는 거죠.
So why you might want to do that is because if you don't want
그렇게 하는 이유는 속도와
your velocities, your momentums to actually
모멘텀이 가중치의 함수가 아니라
be a function of the weights, you
손실의 함수가 되길
want it to be a function of the loss.
원하기 때문입니다.
So if you're trying to traverse your loss landscape more
즉, 실제 가중치 값과 독립적으로
independent of your actual weight values,
손실 지형을 탐색하고 싶을
that's why you might want to separate it.
때 분리하는 겁니다.
But you still might want a regularization term.
하지만 정규화 항은 여전히 필요하죠.
But you don't want it to interfere with the moment
단, 모멘트 계산에 방해가 되지 않게 하려는
calculation.
겁니다.
So this is the specific reason why they do it.
이것이 바로 그렇게 하는 구체적인 이유입니다.
Ultimately, it's empirical you try both
결국 경험적으로 두 가지를 모두 시도해 보고
and you see which one works better.
어느 쪽이 더 나은지 확인하는 겁니다.
But this is why you would do it that way.
이해되셨죠?
OK, cool.
좋습니다.
So we'll talk about learning rates.
이제 학습률에 대해 이야기해 보겠습니다.
So there are different ways in which
학습률을 선택하는 다양한
learning rates can be chosen.
방법이 있습니다.
And sometimes you'll get a very high learning rate
때로는 너무 높은 학습률을
where what will happen is basically
쓰면, 앞서 설명한
your loss will get very large as you oscillate out
것처럼 손실이 매우 커지면서 손실
of the loss landscape, as we described earlier.
지형 밖으로 진동하게 됩니다.
If you have a very low learning rate,
반대로 너무 낮은
your issue is you just converge very slowly.
학습률은 수렴이 매우 느립니다.
If you have a high learning rate but you're not oscillating out,
높은 학습률인데 진동하지는
but you might not be able to converge because you're
않지만, 국소 최소점 주변에서
bumping around the local minimum,
튕기면서 실제로 더
but you're not actually able to get
낮은 값으로 수렴하지
any lower in because your learning rate is too high.
못할 수도 있습니다.
And ideally, a good learning rate
이상적인 학습률은
would have this property where it causes your loss
시간이 지남에 따라 손실을
to decrease quickly over time, but then you
빠르게 감소시키고, 계속
see continued improvements as you continue to train the model.
훈련하면서도 지속적인 개선이 이루어지는 특성을 가집니다.
In reality, actually, depending on the situation, a lot of these
실제로는 상황에 따라 이런 여러 학습률이 모두
could be good learning rates, and also
괜찮을 수 있고, 훈련 단계에
depending on the step in training,
따라서도 달라질 수
which is the final thing we'll discuss in lecture today.
있습니다. 오늘 강의의 마지막 주제가 바로 이것입니다.
So you can actually change your learning rate
즉, 모델을 훈련하면서 학습률을
as you train your model.
바꿀 수 있습니다.
You don't need to always have a fixed learning rate or step
항상 고정된 학습률이나 스텝 크기를 가질 필요는
size.
없습니다.
And pretty much all modern deep learning,
그리고 거의 모든 최신 딥러닝, 즉 최고의
like all the best models coming out,
모델들은 학습 중에 학습률을
have different ways they vary the learning
다양하게 조절하는
rate during training.
방법을 가지고 있습니다.
So one really simple way you could do it is after a fixed
가장 간단한 방법 중 하나는 고정된
number of iterations, you just take 1/10 of the learning rate
반복 횟수 후에 학습률을 1/10로 줄이고 계속 학습하는
and you continue training.
것입니다.
So this can resolve the issue of where your learning rate is
이 방법은 학습률이 너무 높아 더 이상 수렴하지 못하는
too high for you to be able to converge any further,
문제를 해결할 수 있어서, 학습률을 줄이면
so then you reduce it, and you're able to get lower
손실 함수의 낮은 지점까지
into the loss landscape.
도달할 수 있습니다.
And this is really commonly used when training ResNets.
이 방법은 ResNet을 학습할 때 매우 흔히 사용됩니다.
So that's a very popular type of convolutional neural network,
ResNet은 나중에 강의에서 다룰 매우
which we'll discuss later in the course.
인기 있는 합성곱 신경망 종류입니다.
Another thing you could do is cosine learning rate decay.
또 다른 방법은 코사인 학습률 감소(cosine learning rate decay)입니다.
So this one is also extremely popular.
이 방법도 매우 인기가 많습니다.
So here you have--
여기서는 기본적으로 코사인
basically, this is like half of a cosine wave
파형의 절반처럼,
where you're starting at your maximum learning rate here.
최대 학습률에서 시작합니다.
And then you go down to 0 to the end.
그리고 끝까지 0으로 내려갑니다.
And it follows this 1.2 cosine shape,
이것은 1.2 코사인 형태를 따르며, 계산
and here's the formula for calculating it.
공식도 여기 있습니다.
I won't go into too many details,
자세한 내용은 다루지 않겠지만,
but the basic idea is there's a ton of different ways to do it.
기본 아이디어는 다양한 방법이 있다는 것입니다.
When your loss uses a cosine learning rate scheduler,
코사인 학습률 스케줄러를 사용할 때는
you'll often see a shape like this
학습 중간에 좋은
where you get pretty good continued gains
성능 향상이 나타나는 이런 형태를 자주
in the middle part of training.
볼 수 있습니다.
But the basic idea is that the actual shape
하지만 기본적으로 학습 중 손실 함수의
of your loss during training will highly depend
형태는 어떤 스케줄러를
on what scheduler you use.
쓰느냐에 크게 좌우됩니다.
So this is the basic idea I'm trying to convey.
이것이 제가 전달하려는 기본 아이디어입니다.
It looks very different, for example, than this one,
예를 들어, 학습 중에
where you can literally see where we're taking 1/10
학습률을 1/10로 줄이는 이
of the learning rate during training.
방법과는 손실 곡선 모양이 매우 다릅니다.
Another thing you do is just a linear learning rate decay.
또 다른 방법은 단순히 선형 학습률 감소를 하는 것입니다.
So it just follows a straight line.
즉, 직선을 따라 감소하는 거죠.
You could do an inverse square root, et cetera, et cetera.
역제곱근 등 다양한 방법도 가능합니다.
There's basically, an unlimited number of ways
사실 학습 중에 학습률을
you could mess with your learning rate during training.
조절하는 방법은 무한히 많습니다.
And depending on the type of model you're training
그리고 훈련하는 모델 종류나 가장
and depending on what works best,
잘 맞는 방법에 따라
you just choose the one that works best.
최적의 방법을 선택하면 됩니다.
But here are some ones you could try that could perform well
여기 여러분 환경에서 잘 작동할 수 있는
in your setting.
몇 가지 방법을 소개합니다.
Also a really, really popular strategy
또한 매우 인기 있는 전략은 선형
is to have a linear warm up.
워밍업을 하는 것입니다.
So instead of just starting at your maximum learning rate,
최대 학습률에서 바로 시작하는
you spend a fixed number of iterations
대신, 일정한 반복 횟수
to linearly warm up to whatever your maximum value is, and then
동안 선형적으로 최대값까지 워밍업한 후, 이후에는 원하는
you go about doing whatever scheduler you had afterwards.
스케줄러를 적용하는 방식입니다.
So for example linear warm up, and then this
예를 들어 선형 워밍업 후 역제곱근
would be like the inverse square root.
스케줄러를 사용하는 경우가 있습니다.
Or linear warm up and then--
또는 선형 워밍업 후 코사인
cosine is a very popular setup for training models.
스케줄러를 사용하는데, 코사인은 모델 훈련에 매우 인기 있는 설정입니다.
One final thing is that there is this empirical rule of thumb
마지막으로, 경험적으로 알려진 규칙 중에 선형
called the linear scaling hypothesis or linear scaling
스케일링 가설 또는 선형 스케일링 법칙 같은 것이
law, or something like that.
있습니다.
I forget the name.
정확한 명칭은 기억이 나지 않네요.
I think it's linear scaling law, where
아마 선형 스케일링
it shows that if you increase your batch
법칙일 텐데, 배치 크기나
size or the number of training examples per update by n,
업데이트 당 훈련 샘플 수를 n배 늘리면 학습률도
you should also scale your learning rate by n.
n배로 늘려야 한다는 내용입니다.
So as you increase your batch size,
즉, 배치 크기를
you should increase your learning rate directly
늘릴 때 학습률도 비례해서 증가시켜야
proportionally.
한다는 거죠.
So I think the math behind this is a bit involved,
이 이론의 수학적 배경은 다소 복잡하고,
and also it's more of an empirical rule of thumb.
경험적인 규칙에 가깝습니다.
So people have tried to show mathematical proofs
그래서 사람들이 왜 이 방법이 유용할 수 있는지 수학적 증명을
for why this could be useful.
시도해 본 경우도 있습니다.
But based on the variation of gradients in your batch
하지만 배치 내 그래디언트의 변동과 배치당 계산하는
and the number of gradients you calculate per batch,
그래디언트 수 등에 따라 다르지만, 실제로 많은
et cetera, but really this is just
문제에서 경험적으로 이
shown empirically to be true for a large number of problems.
방법이 효과적임이 입증되었습니다.
So this is a good rule of thumb.
그래서 이것은 좋은 경험적 규칙입니다.
If you have a winning recipe but you
만약 좋은 방법을
want to increase the batch size, then also
찾았는데 배치 크기를 늘리고
increase your learning rate by the same amount.
싶다면, 학습률도 같은 비율로 늘리면 됩니다.
Cool.
좋죠.
And then the final thing I'll touch upon very briefly
그리고 마지막으로 아주 간단히 언급할
is this idea of second-order optimization, which
것은, 누군가가 앞서 질문했던 Hessian을
uses the Hessian that someone asked
사용하는 2차 최적화
a question about earlier, too.
방법입니다.
So we won't talk about this very much in depth,
이 부분을 깊게 다루지는 않겠지만,
but just to let you know this exists.
존재한다는 것만 알려드리겠습니다.
It's not something we cover in the course very much.
이 과정에서 많이 다루지는 않습니다.
But the basic idea is right now we're using the gradient
기본 아이디어는 지금 우리가
to form a linear approximation of basically,
그래디언트를 사용해 손실
where's the downward direction where
함수의 하강
we're trying to traverse this loss landscape.
방향을 선형 근사하는 겁니다.
And we just look at the direction
그 방향을 보고 일반적인 한
and we take a general step in that direction.
걸음을 내딛는 거죠.
And we added fancy things like momentum and the RMSProp
그리고 모멘텀이나 RMSProp 같은 기법을 추가해 가파른
where we're decelerating along the steep directions.
방향에서는 속도를 줄이기도 했습니다.
But this is the basic idea.
이게 기본적인 아이디어입니다.
We're using this gradient at each time step.
매 시간마다 이 그래디언트를 사용하고 있죠.
The idea of the Hessian is instead of using the gradient,
Hessian의 아이디어는
you basically try to fit a quadratic or a second degree
그래디언트 대신 그 지점에서의 도함수나 Hessian을 이용해 함수에
polynomial to your function based on the derivatives
2차 다항식, 즉 이차
at that point or the Hessians at that point.
곡선을 맞추는 겁니다.
And you then try to find the minimum this way.
그리고 그 방법으로 최소값을 찾으려 하는 거죠.
And in certain optimization problems
특정 최적화 문제에서는 이 방법이
this actually works extremely well.
매우 잘 작동합니다.
But generally, we don't use it in deep learning
하지만 일반적으로 딥러닝에서는 두 가지 이유
because it requires two things.
때문에 잘 사용하지 않습니다.
So one, you have to do this Taylor series expansion,
우선, 테일러 급수 전개를
whereas right now we're just doing the first part where we're
해야 하는데, 지금은
taking the derivative, but you would
미분만 하고 있지만
need to be able to calculate the second mixed derivatives, which
두 번째 혼합 미분도 계산할 수
is already maybe difficult. And then on top of that,
있어야 합니다. 이게 이미 어려울 수 있습니다. 게다가 모델의 모든 파라미터에 대한 혼합
this mixed derivative of all of your parameters
미분이 다른 모든 파라미터에 대해 계산되면, 수백만
in your model by all the other parameters in your model
또는 수십억 개의 파라미터를
can get very large as you have these many million or billion
가진 신경망에서는 매우 커질
parameter neural networks.
수 있습니다.
So in practice, we don't use it because these matrices become
그래서 실제로는 이 행렬들이 너무 커지기 때문에 사용하지
way too large.
않습니다.
And so you run out of memory on your computer
만약 시도하면 컴퓨터 메모리가
if you try to run it.
부족해질 겁니다.
Specifically, you're on a GPU memory.
특히 GPU 메모리에서 그렇습니다.
But if you're training a smaller model
하지만 작은 모델을
or if you're OK with spending much more time to get better
훈련하거나 더 나은 최적화 단계를 위해 더 많은 시간을 투자할
steps towards your minimum, then maybe you
수 있다면 이 방법을 고려해볼
want to look into this.
수 있습니다.
Depends on the problem set, but for smaller models
문제에 따라 다르지만, 작은 모델에서는
this actually works quite well.
실제로 꽤 잘 작동합니다.
But for these large neural networks we're training,
하지만 우리가 훈련하는 대규모
we basically never do this due to the memory restrictions.
신경망에서는 메모리 제한 때문에 거의 사용하지 않습니다.
And all the time you spent computationally
그리고 헤시안 행렬 계산 등에
trying to calculate the Hessian, et cetera,
소요되는 계산 시간을 데이터 더 많이
you would rather just see more data during training.
보는 데 쓰는 게 낫습니다.
All right.
좋습니다.
So some, I guess, concluding thoughts for you
여러분께 도움이 될 만한 몇 가지 마무리 생각을
all that can be useful.
말씀드리겠습니다.
So Adam or AdamW is a really good default choice
Adam이나 AdamW는 새로운 문제에 대해 첫
for training your first model if you're working on a new problem.
모델을 훈련할 때 정말 좋은 기본 선택입니다.
In a domain, I would recommend it.
특정 도메인에서 추천합니다.
And it could even work OK, even if you do constant learning
그리고 일정한 학습률로도 괜찮게 작동할 수
rate.
있습니다.
So usually people will try Adam AdamW with constant learning
보통 사람들은 일정한 학습률이나 선형 워밍업,
rate or with a linear warm up, and then a cosine
그리고 코사인 감쇠를 조합해서
decay those are like a really popular combination.
Adam이나 AdamW를 시도합니다. 이 조합이 매우 인기가 많습니다.
Also, I think, SGD and momentum can sometimes outperform Adam.
또한, SGD와 모멘텀은 때때로 Adam보다 더 좋은 성능을 낼 수 있습니다.
But the tricky thing is because you generally
하지만 까다로운 점은 일반적으로 값을 더 많이
have to tune the values more, so you
조정해야 한다는 겁니다. RMSProp
have to try many more learning rates because you
항이 없기 때문에 급격한 방향을 고려할
don't have this RMSProp term to account
수 없어서 더 많은 학습률을
for the steep directions.
시도해야 합니다.
And also you might have to try different scheduling values,
또한 다른 스케줄링 값을 시도해야 할 수도 있는데,
whereas in practice, Adam's best by test.
실제로는 Adam이 테스트에서 가장 좋습니다.
People have tried it a bunch of different domains
사람들이 여러 분야에서 많이 시도해봤고
and it works very well.
아주 잘 작동합니다.
It's very adaptive to the loss landscape.
손실 함수 지형에 매우 적응적입니다.
If you're doing a full-batch update where you're already,
만약 전체 배치 업데이트를 하고
at each step, you can fit basically,
있고, 각
your entire training set into your batch size,
단계에서 기본적으로 전체 훈련 세트를
you might want to look beyond first-order optimization
배치 크기에 맞출 수 있다면,
into second-order and beyond, because it seems like your data
1차 최적화보다 2차 이상
set's not very large, or maybe your model is not very large,
최적화를 고려하는 게 좋습니다.
and you could potentially, benefit
데이터 세트가
from having these non-linear update steps
크지 않거나 모델이 크지 않은 경우,
and computing more sophisticated strategies for going down trying
비선형 업데이트 단계와 더 정교한 하강 전략을
to find the minimum here.
계산하는 것이 이득일 수 있습니다.
Yeah, so I think we're essentially
네, 사실상 강의는
done with the lecture.
여기까지입니다.
I'll give some slides about looking forward.
앞으로의 내용을 다룬 슬라이드를 보여드리겠습니다.
So how do we optimize more complex functions
이번 강의에서 다룬 선형 모델보다 더
than linear models, which is what we covered in this lecture?
복잡한 함수를 어떻게 최적화할 수 있을까요?
And next lecture specifically, we'll
다음 강의에서는
be looking at neural networks, which is very exciting topic.
특히 신경망을 다룰 텐데, 매우 흥미로운 주제입니다.
A neural network, the we'll discuss in class, is basically,
수업에서 다룰 신경망은 기본적으로 두
you have two of these weight matrices
개의 가중치 행렬이 있고, 각
now, one for each layer.
층마다 하나씩 있습니다.
And you have something called a non-linearity sort of stuck
그리고 그 사이에 비선형성이라는 것이 끼어
between.
있습니다.
So in this case, the most common--
가장 흔한, 아니 가장 단순한
sorry, not the most common, but the most simple
비선형 함수는 ReLU
one is just this ReLU function, which you'll learn about more.
함수인데, 나중에 더 배우게 될 겁니다.
But the basic idea is now we have two weight matrices,
기본 아이디어는 이제 두
and we have this additional function
개의 가중치 행렬이 있고,
that's done in between the weight matrix calculations.
그 사이에 추가 함수가 계산된다는 겁니다.
This is nice because, as I said, it's nonlinear.
이게 좋은 점은, 말씀드렸듯이 비선형이라는 겁니다.
So if we're trying to build a linear classifier to classify
만약 이런 데이터를 선형 분류기로 분류하려
data like this, you'll run into an issue
하면, 파란 점과 빨간
where the blue points and the red points
점이 선형적으로 분리되지
are not linearly separable.
않는 문제가 생깁니다.
But maybe there's some transformations we can do
하지만 어떤 변환을 하거나
or through many layers of a model,
여러 층을 거치면서
we can eventually transform the data
데이터를 선형으로 분리 가능한
into a way in which it is separable by a line, which
형태로 변환할 수 있습니다. 그게
would be our then final layer of the model.
모델의 마지막 층이 되는 거죠.
[AUDIO LOGO]
[AUDIO LOGO]